好的，是时候开始了。
Alright, actually, it's time to start.
好的，就想 Frans 所说的，
Alright, okay as Frans were saying for you,
随时可以打断进行提问，
feel free to interrupt with questions
并且可以让你的摄像头开着，
and feel free to leave your camera on,
这样我们就可以看到彼此。
so that we can see each other people.
这将是另一节关于日志的课，
This is going to be another lecture about logging,
这一次对 Linux 中现在的日志系统的研究，
this time a case study of the current logging system in Linux's
ext3 文件系统，
ext3 file system,
它应用非常广泛，
which is extremely widely used
而且我们尝试涉足一些现实世界的设计问题，
and we'll try to dip into some of the kind of real-world design problems,
高性能文件系统必须处理的，
that a high performance file system has to deal with,
当它将日志添加到文件系统时。
when it adds logging to the file system.
我要花几分钟，
I'm just gonna go spend a few minutes,
回顾一下为什么我们谈论日志，
basically reviewing why we're talking about logging,
我们觉得日志很重要的原因是，
the reason, that we feel logging is pretty important is that,
它是一个非常成功和重要的想法，
it's been a tremendously successful and important idea,
日志是一种神奇的方式，
it's almost like logging is kind of a magic way
将崩溃恢复添加到几乎任何现有存储系统。
to add crash recovery to any almost any existing storage system.
在很多方面是不相关的，
Sort of, in many ways pretty orthogonal
无论你想存储的是什么。
to whatever it is you're actually trying to store.
所以，你可以看到日志应用于大量不同的存储情况，
And so you see logging applied in a huge number of different storage situations,
当然有数据库和文件系统，
certainly databases and file systems,
而且还有许多非常专业的系统，
but also many very specialized systems,
它们需要存储东西并在崩溃后恢复。
that need to store things and recover after crashes.
你还可以看到在分布式系统中大量使用日志，
You also see logging used a lot in distributed systems,
作为从故障中恢复的一种方式，
as a way of organizing the recovery from failure,
因为与其他东西相比，日志是一种结构化的方式，
because among other things, logging is a structured way of saying,
这是崩溃前发生的所有事情，
well here's all the things that happened just before the crash
如果我们能理解它们，
and if we can understand them,
也许我们就能更容易地从崩溃中恢复。
then maybe we can recover from the crash more easily.
再加上有大量有趣的东西可以细想，
Plus there's a huge amount of interesting stuff to chew on,
当你尝试构建高性能日志系统时。
when you try to build high performance logging systems.
就像我几分钟前提到的，
And as I mentioned a few minutes ago,
作为术语，当我们讨论日志时，
just as a point of terminology when we talk about log,
它谈论的事情和今天的读物完全一样，
it's talking about this exactly the same thing as today's reader,
读物说的是 journal 这个词，
reading was talking about when it said use the word journal,
它们是同义词。
they're just synonyms.
此外，今天的读物谈到了
And furthermore the today's reading talked about
在 ext2 中增加 journal ，
adding a journal to ext2,
结果文件系统的现代名称是 ext3 ，
the modern name for the resulting file system is ext3,
我就是这么称呼它的。
which is how I'm going to refer to it.
好的，我想花点时间，
Okay, I want to spend,
我要谈论 ext3 的方式是
the way I'm going to talk about ext3 is
将它与 xv6 进行某种程度的对比，
by contrasting it to some extent with xv6
并解释 ext3 修复一些性能问题的方法，
and explaining ways in which ext3 fixes some performance problems,
xv6 日志具有的问题，
that xv6 logging has
并在过程中改变一些语义，
and along the way changes a few of the semantic of,
在崩溃中会发生什么。
what happens during crashes.
好的，这是 xv6 的日志回顾，
Alright, so this is xv6 log review,
应该记住，
should remember,
这个 xv6 的文件系统磁盘，
this disk, the file system disk for xv6,
你可以认为它有两个部分，
there's you know you can think of it as having two parts,
它上面有一个文件系统树，
it's got a file system tree on it,
有一个根目录，
with a root directory
在根目录下，可能还有其他目录，
and under the root directory, maybe there's other directories in those,
可能是目录一和目录二，
this might be directory one and directory two,
我们可以认为文件系统只是一个数据结构，
we can think of this as file system is just a data structure,
是一个树形结构的数据结构，
is a tree structure data structure,
可能它有文件，位于目录中，
may be it has files, sitting in the directories
每个文件中都有一些块编号，
and each file has a block number of a bunch of blocks in it
还有一些其他的数据，不是树形结构，
and there's some other data, that's not really tree structure,
比如，这里有一个位图，表示每个块，
like, there's the bitmap, that indicates for every block,
它是空闲的还是分配的。
whether that block is you know free or allocated.
索引结点，目录内容和位图块
And the inodes and the directory contents and the bitmap blocks
被称为元数据，
are going to refer to as metadata,
对比保存文件内容的块，我们称为文件内容块。
contrast blocks that hold file content which we'll call file content blocks.
好的，那么除了文件系统，
Okay, so in addition to the file system,
xv6 日志，在磁盘的开头附近，
xv6 log, near the beginning of the disk
xv6 日志相对简单，
and xv6 log is relatively simple,
它有 header 块，
it has this header block,
然后是一些区块，包含块的更新版本。
and then some number of blocks, that contain updated versions of blocks
来自文件系统数据块和元数据块。
from the file system data blocks and metadata blocks.
在这个开始的 header 块中，
And in this [initial] header block,
有一个块编号，
there's a block numbers,
那些日志中的块应该写入的位置，
where these blocks in the log ought to be written to,
比如，第一个应该去块 17 ，
like maybe the first one should go to block 17
然后是 29 ，无论是什么。
and then 29, who knows whatever it maybe.
然后在计算机中，
And then in the computer,
我们有一些用户进程可能调用 write create ，
we have some user process, that's maybe calling write, create,
某些其他修改文件系统的系统调用。
some other system call that modifies the file system.
而且，计算机中有一个块缓存，
And, there's a block cache in the computer
最初 write 只会进入块缓存，
and initially the writes just go to the block cache,
它只是磁盘上块的拷贝，
it's just copies of block from the disk,
所以最初 write 更新文件块或索引节点
so initially write updates file blocks or inodes
或其他写入到那里的任何东西，
or whatever those writes go there,
然后在操作结束时，
and then at the end of an operation,
这些数据块被复制到日志中，
these blocks are copied to the log
当我们复制完所有数据块时，
and when we've copied all the block's log,
然后我们将块编号写入 header 块，
then we write the block numbers to the header block,
表示这个事务更新已完成。
to indicate that this transactions where is updates is complete.
在文件系统的代码中，你会看到，
And in the code for the file system, you'll see,
每个修改文件系统的系统调用，
that every system call that modifies the file system,
某处有一个 begin_op ，
somewhere has a begin_op,
表示将要开始对文件系统的一组更新，
which says about to start a group of updates to the file system,
在我做完之前，不要做它们中的任何一个，
please don't do any of them until I finished,
所以我们有，
so we have
然后有些读取和写入块，
and then there's a bunch of block reads writes
然后是 end_op ，
and then end_op,
它告诉文件系统日志系统
which tells the file system logging system
完全完成我要执行的所有写入。
completely done all the writes I'm gonna do.
所以，在 begin_op 和 end_op 之间，
So between the begin_op and the end_op,
写入仅进入缓存，
the writes only go to the cache
当系统调用进行 end_op 调用时，
and when the system call makes this end_op call,
然后，文件系统将修改后的块从缓存复制到日志中。
then the file system copies the modified blocks from the cache into the log.
在将所有这些修改过的数据块写入日志后，
And after it's written all these modified blocks into the log,
只有这样，文件系统才会将块编号写入
only then, does the file system write the block numbers
单个磁盘中，写入到 header 块。
in a single disk, right, to the header block.
这称为提交点，
And that's called the commit point,
这是文件系统将这些块编号写入 header 块之前的点，
this is the point before the file system wrote these block numbers to the header block,
如果发生了崩溃，
if the crash had happened,
这些写入都不会应用，
then none of these writes would have been applied,
在崩溃和重新启动之后。
after the crash and reboot.
在文件系统写入 header 块的块编号之后，
After the file system writes these block numbers of the header block,
在这个写入完成后，
after that this write is complete,
那么可以保证，
then it's guaranteed that,
即使在这一点上发生崩溃，
even if there's a crash at this point,
恢复软件也会查看日志，
the recovery software will look at the log,
看到在 header 块中有块编号，
see that there's block numbers in the header block
将这些在 header 块中提到的块写入
and write all these blocks that are mentioned in the header block
它们在文件系统的原位置。
to their home locations in the file system.
所以这里是一种技术，
And so what's going on here is a technique
允许所有的写入，
to allow all of the writes,
在 begin_op 和 end_op 之间的系统调用中发生
that happen in the system call between the begin_op and the end_op
是原子的，关于崩溃，
to be atomic with respect to crashes,
要么所有的事情都发生，
that is either all of them happen,
因为文件系统在崩溃之前只写 header 块，
because the file system got as far as writing the header block before the crash
或者它们都没有发生，
or none of them happen,
因为崩溃发生在文件系统写入 header 块之前。
because the crash happened before the file system wrote the header block.
所以重要的是，在崩溃和重启之后，
And so it's important that after a crash and restart,
有一些恢复软件可以运行来读取日志，
there's some recovery software that runs that reads the log,
查看 header 块，
looks at the header block
并确定块编号是不是在 header 块中，
and decides is the header block actually block numbers in it or not,
如果是，
if it does,
写操作可能会将所有这些数据块重写到它们的原位置，
writes possibly rewrite all these blocks to their home locations,
如果 header 块中没有任何块编号，
if the header blocks doesn't have any block numbers in it,
则恢复软件不会执行任何操作。
then the recovery software does nothing.
关于这个快速复习，有什么问题？
Any questions about this quick review?
好的，有几点非常重要，
Okay, there's a couple of super important points,
记住 xv6 ，甚至大多数日志记录系统。
to remember about xv6 and indeed most logging systems.
一个是 xv6 以及所有日志系统
One is that xv6 all logging systems,
都遵循所谓的预写规则。
essentially obey what's called the write-ahead rule.
也就是说，当你有一些操作的一些写入，
That is whenever you have a bunch of writes done by some operation
而这些写入都需要是原子的，
and those writes all need to be atomic,
系统必须将所有这些更新的的数据写入日志，
the system has to write all of these updated, all the updated data to the log,
在允许将应用这些更新之前，
before it is allowed to apply any of those updates
到文件系统中的原位置，
to the home locations in the file system,
也就是说，我们需要预先声明所有更新，
that is that we're required to sort of pre declare all the updates
我们想要是原子的，
that we want to have the atomic,
在日志中预先声明它们，
pre declare them in the log,
在我们可以将任何一个应用到文件系统之前，
before we can apply any of them to the file system,
即所谓的预写规则。
as called the write-ahead rule.
这是日志允许崩溃恢复的基础。
This is really the foundation of how logging allows crash recovery.
所以，预先规则允许这些更新
So the write-head rule allows this collection of updates
相对于崩溃看起来是原子的。
to appear atomic with respect to crashes.
还有一条我没有谈到的规则，
There's another rule I haven't talked about,
那就是我们不能释放或重复使用日志，
which is that we can't free or reuse the log,
xv6 对每个系统调用反复使用日志，
you know we xv6 use the log over and over again,
每个系统调用一次，
ones for every system call,
我们不允许重用日志，
we cannot allow to reuse the log,
在日志中的所有写入
until all of the writes that are in the log
都已经写入磁盘上的原位置之前。
have actually been written to their home locations on the disk.
所以这也是我所说的释放法则，
So this is also what I called freeing rule,
也就是说，我们不能覆盖或重用日志，直到，
which says, we can't overwrite or reuse the log until,
或者部分日志包含指定事务，
or the part of log that holds a particular transaction,
一组需要原子的写入，
you know set of writes that need to be atomic,
我们不能重用这部分日志，
we can't reuse that part of the log
直到所有写入，
until all the writes,
不是部分日志，
that are not part of the log,
所有它们都被反映到
all of them have been reflected into
文件系统中的原位置。
the actual home location in the file system.
所以， xv6 中的事务，
So the deal in xv6 that,
end_op 触发了大量工作，
what end_op does actually triggers a whole lot of work, first
而文件系统，正如我提到的那样，写入所有日志，
and the file system, you know as I mentioned writes all the logs,
日志写入 header 日志，写入 header 块，
the log writes the header log, writes the header block,
然后文件系统将所有这些块写入它们的原始位置，
and then the file system writes all these blocks their home locations,
这是假设不发生崩溃的情况下。
this is assuming no crash which is the ordinary case.
所以文件系统第二次写入时，
So then the file system write the second time
所有块到它们在磁盘上的原位置，
you know all these blocks to the home locations on the disk,
然后在所有原位置都被更新之后，
and then after all the home locations have been updated,
只有在那时，文件系统才继续，
only then does the file system go,
xv6 文件系统从 header 块中擦除这些块编号，
xv6 file system erase these block numbers from the header block,
表明我们已完成这个事务，
to indicate that we're done with this transaction
并且可以重用日志。
and we can reuse the log.
删除块编号是至关重要的，
And it's critical to erase the block numbers,
在向日志中写入任何新内容之前，
before writing anything new to the log,
因为我们不想处于这样的情况，
because we wouldn't want to be in a position,
在 header 中先前事务的一些块编号，
where there were some block numbers from a previous transaction in the header,
但是块来自新的事务，
but blocks from a new transaction,
可能是不同的块编号在日志中，
presumably different block numbers sitting in the log,
因为崩溃可能会应用这些内容
because then a crash would might apply these contents
应用留在 header 块中过期的块编号。
to the stale block numbers left over in the header block.
所以你先删除 header 块，
So if you erase the header block first,
所以这是一条释放规则，
so this is freeing rule,
规定在我们被允许从日志中删除事务之前，
that says before we're allowed to erase a transaction from the log,
我们必须将所有这些块写入文件系统。
we have to write all these blocks to the file system.
好的，这样做的最终效果是
Okay, so the net effect of this is
复杂的或需要多次写入的文件系统更新，
to make file system updates which can be complicated and require many writes
实际效果是使每个系统调用是原子的，
and the net effect is to make each system call essentially be atomic,
对于崩溃来说，全部写入或没有写入。
all its writes or none of them with respect to crashes.
好的，日志方案通向 Linux 的桥梁是
Okay, so, so the sort of bridge to Linux is logging scheme,
是关于 xv6 日志有什么问题，
is the question of what's wrong with xv6 logging,
为什么 Linux 不使用与 xv6 完全相同的方案。
why doesn't Linux just use exactly the same scheme, the xv6 does.
答案是它很慢，
And the answer is basically that it's slow,
xv6 方案相当慢，
the xv6 scheme is quite slow,
每个系统调用，
every system call,
在 xv6 中，比如 write 或 create 这样的系统调用返回前，
before a system call like write or create can return in xv6,
我刚才说的这些东西都要完成，
all of this stuff I just talked about has to complete,
所以，在你的文件创建系统调用返回用户空间之前，
so before your file creation system call can return to user space,
它必须完成 end_op 所做的所有工作，
the it has to finish all the stuff that end_op does,
这意味着将每个块写入日志，
which means write every block to the log,
写入 header 块，
write the header block,
写入所有块到这里的位置，
write all those blocks to the locations here,
并删除 header 块，
and erase the header block,
然后就可以返回了。
and then you can return.
在此期间，
And during that time,
不仅每个系统调用需要很长时间，
not only does each system call take a long time,
而且文件系统中不会发生其他事情，
but nothing else can happen in the file system,
当所有系统调用提交，
while any system call is committing
将其块写入其原位置。
and then writing its blocks to their home location.
所以系统调用一次只发生一个，
So the system calls really occur one at a time
并且每个系统调用都需要许多磁盘写入。
and each system call requires many disk writes.
每个系统调用必须
And the technical term for every system call has to
等待其所有磁盘写入完成的术语称为同步。
wait for all of its disk writes to complete is called synchronous.
嗯，这个，可能拼写不一样。
Um, this, probably spelled differently from that.
无论如何，对于磁盘来说， xv6 系统调用是同步的。
Anyway, xv6 system call are synchronous with respect to disk.
所以它们非常慢，
So they're very very slow,
对于机械磁盘更是慢的可怕，
and they were horribly slow with mechanical hard drives,
因为每一次写入都需要 10 毫秒。
because each write you know basically take ten milliseconds.
我们谈论的是许多写入的系统调用，
We're talking about many writes for system calls,
所以， xv6 在一秒钟内只能执行几个文件系统修改系统调用。
so xv6 could only do a few file system modifying system calls for a second.
我想如果我们运行 xv6 固态硬盘速度更快，
And I wonder if we ran xv6 solid state drive to be faster,
但仍然没有达到应有的效率。
but still not nearly as efficient as it could be.
另一个需要注意的更详细的事情是，
Another more detail thing to notice about this is
每个块在 xv6 方案中写入两次，
that every block is written twice in the xv6 scheme,
它第一次写入日志，
it's written once to the log
然后第二次写入磁盘。
and then at second time to the disk.
所以这也是，
And so this is also something that,
有好的理由，
there's good reasons for that,
但是 ext3 可以部分修复这个问题。
but it's something that ext3 partially fixes.
好的，那么在 Linux 上，
Okay, so on the Linux is,
根据今天的论文，它是，
under the today's reading and it's sort of,
我要谈谈这个 ext3 文件系统，
I'm going to talk about the this ext3 file system,
今天的论文经过几年的变化，
which is what the today's reading had turned into a few years later
在更多的发展之后，
after a bit more development,
并得到广泛应用。
and was widely used.
好的，所以 ext3 ，
Okay, so ext3,
它是对之前的无日志文件系统的修改。
it's actually a modification previous logless file system.
所以，他们真的利用现有存储系统，
So they really did play this game of taking existing storage system
并在它上面加上日志，
and sort of layering logging on top of it,
使底层 ext2 文件系统几乎没有修改，
in a way that left the underlying ext2 file system almost unmodified,
虽然不是完全没有。
although not quite.
所以，从某种意义上说，日志是一种非常容易，
So in a sense, the logging was a very kind of easy,
至少，对它们来说升级很容易。
you know at least in principle, easy upgrade for them.
ex3 保持着类似于 xv6 的数据结构，
Ex3 keeps data structures that are similar to xv6's,
在内存中，有一个块缓存，一个回写缓存，
in memory, there's a block cache, a write back cache,
这里有一些缓存块，
there's a bunch of cache blocks,
其中一些是干净的，
some of them are clean,
因为它们没有被修改，
in the sense that they haven't been modified,
因为它们与磁盘上的内容完全相同，
since you know identical to what's on the disk,
有一些是脏的，
some of them dirty,
它们被写入，
in the sense that they've been written to,
自从从磁盘读取它们，
since they were read from the disk
有一些人是固定的，
and some of them were pinned
因为它们不允许被写回磁盘，
and that they're not allowed to be written back to disk,
因为回写规则，
because of the write back rule,
我是说因为释放规则，预写规则。
I mean because of the freeing rule, the write-ahead rule.
ext2 还维护一些事务信息，
Ext2 also cause maintain some transaction information,
你可以维护多个事务的信息，
you can maintain information actually about multiple transactions
它们在不同运行阶段并行。
that are concurrently in different stages of execution.
所以，可能有许多不同的事务，
So, there might be a number of different transactions,
ext3 系统跟踪着，
that the ext3 system is keeping track of,
每个事务都有一个序列号，
each one, each transaction has a sequence number,
事务系统的一些块编号，
a set of block numbers that the transaction system is
日志系统记住事务修改的块，
logging system is remembering are blocks modified by that transaction,
所以这是一组块编号。
so these are set of block numbers.
这是缓存块，
And this really refers to cache blocks,
因为任何修改至少开始只发生在缓存中。
because any modifications at least initially you know happen only in the cache.
然后是一组被称为 handle 的东西，
And then a set of what are called handles,
它们是有关仍在并发执行的系统调用的信息，
which are information about system calls that are still concurrently executing
并且作为事务的一部分，
and as part of this transaction
以及读取和写入缓存块。
and reading and writing cache blocks.
在磁盘上，
And on the disk, on the disk,
就像 xv6 一样，有通常的文件系统树，
just like xv6, there's the usual file system tree,
索引节点目录块和文件等等，
inode directory blocks and files and whatnot,
还有一些位图块
and there's bitmap blocks
表示每个数据块是否已分配，
indicating you know whether each block is data block is allocated or free
这些就是我所说的文件系统数据块的原位置，
and so these are what I'll be calling the home locations of file system blocks
然后在磁盘的指定部分，是日志。
and then on a sort of designated part of the disk, there's the log.
目前为止，这与 xv6 非常相似，
And so, so far this is pretty similar to xv6,
主要区别在于 ext3 能够
the main difference is the ext3's ability
同时跟踪多个事务
to keep track of multiple transactions at the same time
在其执行的不同阶段。
in different stages of their execution.
现在我想更仔细地看看 ext3 中的日志，
Now, I want to look more closely at what's inside the log in ext3,
与 xv6 日志略有不同。
is a bit different from what's in the xv6 log.
有一种日志格式，
There's a log format,
在日志的开头，有一些东西叫做超级块，
at the beginning of the log, there's something called the super block,
这是日志超级块，
and the super block, this is the log super block
与文件系统的超级块不同。
different from the file system super block.
日志超级块包含日志中第一个有效事务的偏移量和序列号，
The log super block contains the offset and sequence number of the first valid transaction in the log,
所以会有一个偏移量，
so it's gonna have an offset,
只是在日志中的一个字节数，块编号，
just a byte number, block number in the log
然后是这个序列号，
and then this lo- sequence number,
记得我说过每个事务都有自己的序列号，
remember I said that every transaction has its own sequence number,
然后剩下的日志，
and then the rest of the log,
日志只是磁盘上已知大小的一串连续数据块。
the log is just a bunch of sequential blocks on disks of a known size.
每个事务，剩下的日志包含事务，
Every transaction, the rest of the log consists of transactions,
每个事务包含一个描述块，
each transaction consists of a descriptor block,
包含块编号，
which contains block numbers just as in the,
非常像 xv6 中的 header 块。
much like the header block in the xv6.
然后，
And then the set of,
对于每个块编号，
for each of these block numbers,
实际更新的内容块对应于块编号，
the actual updated content block corresponding that block number
最后，对于完成并提交的事务，
and then finally for transaction that's actually finished and committed,
这里会有一个提交块，
there'll be a commit block,
这是日志中一个单独的块。
this is a separate block in the log.
因为可以有多个事务日志，
And because there can be more than one transaction log,
那个提交块后面可能是下一个描述块，
that commit block may be followed by the next transaction's descriptor block
然后是一些数据块，
and then some data blocks
然后也许下一个事务的提交块。
and then maybe the next transmission, transaction's commit block.
所以我们有多个，
So we have multiple,
日志文件可能相当长，
log file can be quite long
并包含多个事务。
and contain many transactions in it.
所以我们可以可以，
So this we can think of this
它们之间的偏移量和序列号，
offset and sequence numbers basically between them,
指向最开始的，
pointing to at the very, the first
编号最小的有效事务日志的开头。
the beginning of the earliest lowest numbered valid transaction log.
这里的一些小细节会很重要，
A little detail here that will become important a little while,
这些是描述符块和提交块，
is that these the descriptor blocks and the commit blocks,
为了能够将它们与数据块区分，
in order to be able to help distinguish them from data, from data blocks,
如果它们在崩溃和恢复后扫描日志时，
if when they're scanning log after a crash and recovery,
提交块的描述以魔数开始，
the description of the commit blocks start with a magic number,
它是一个 32 位数，
which is just some 32 bit number,
在数据中不太可能发生，
that is unlikely to occur in data,
帮助日志软件区分描述符和提交块与数据块。
and that helps the log software distinguish descriptor and commit blocks from data blocks.
好的，记住这个结构，
Okay, with this in mind, with this structure in mind,
我要谈谈 ext3 获得良好性能的高级方法。
I'm going to talk about the high-level the ways, that ext3 gets good performance.
有三个主要原因。
And there's really three main.
但是，有一个问题，
But, a question,
是否有可能至少该系统在提交块之前有描述符块，
is it possible for at least this system to have a descriptor block before they commit block,
比如两个事务同时进行。
let's say two transactions going on at the same time.
日志中可以有多个事务。
There can be multiple transactions in the log.
在下一个事务开始之前，这个事务完成。
That's a transaction to finish before the next one can start.
是的，我们正在讨论这件事，
Yeah, we're talking a moment about that,
但是是这样的，
but it is the case,
是的，一次只有一个未完成事务，
yes, that there's there's only one open transaction at a time,
这张图片不太合适，
and this is really not quite the right picture for that,
因为当前打开的事务，
because the current open transaction,
当前打开的事务是系统调用正在向其中执行写入的事务，
the current open transaction is the transaction into which system calls are performing their writes
所以当前打开的事务只存在于内存中，
and so the current open transaction really only exists in memory,
因为当前的系统调用是更新，
and because current system calls are sort of updating,
它们只是更新内存中的文件系统块缓存块，
their just updating block the cached block file system blocks in memory,
当 ext3 系统决定结束当前打开的事务时，
when the ext3 system decides to finished the current open transaction,
在它决定结束时，
you know after it decides to finish it,
它会做两件事，
it'll do two things,
一个是它启动一个新的打开的事务，
one is it will start a new open transaction,
也就是下一个事务，
which will be the next transaction
然后它写入刚刚完成的事务，
and it will then write the the just finished transaction,
开始将刚刚完成的事务写入磁盘，
start writing with just finished transactions to disk,
可能需要相当长的时间。
may actually take quite a while.
所以，整个故事是，
So, so you know the full story is that,
有一些更老的事务在磁盘上，
there's a bunch of older transactions on disk,
所有都是关闭的，
that all of which are closed
加上一个在内存中打开的事务。
plus one open transaction really only exists in memory.
并且至少最开始，
And at least initially,
磁盘上的这些事务
these transactions that are on disk,
可能仅以日志记录的形式存在，
may only exist in the form of the log records
还没有写到它们的原地址，
and haven't initially at least been written to their home locations
然后一段时间后，
and then after a while in the background,
从最早的事务开始，
the starting with the oldest transaction,
日志系统会写入，
the logging system will you know write these,
将日志中的这些更新块写入它们的原位置，
update blocks in the log to their home locations
然后，一旦每个完整的事务完成，
and then once that's been done for each complete transaction,
然后，日志系统可以释放并重用日志中的这些空间，
then the logging system can free and reuse this space in the log
所以这是一个环形的日志，
and so this is really a circular log,
当你到达日志末尾时，
when you get to the end of the log,
日志系统开始使用开头的块，
the logging system start using the blocks at the beginning
你必须释放它们，
and you have to free them,
将它们写入原位置来释放这些块，
free these blocks by writing them to their home locations,
然后才能使用它们。
before it can be used.
好的。
Okay.
好的，有三种方式可以让 ext3 获得良好性能，
Okay, so there's three ways that the system gets ext3 gets good performance,
一个是它有异步系统调用，
one is that it has asynchronous system calls,
也就是系统调用在写磁盘之前就返回，
that is system calls return before they've written the disk,
系统调用只是更新内存中的缓存块，然后返回，
the system call just updates cache blocks in memory, and then returns,
不需要写入磁盘，
never never has to write the disk,
不需要等待磁盘写入，
never has to wait for disk writes,
虽然需要等待磁盘读取。
although may wait for disk reads.
下一个获得高性能方法是批处理，
The next big idea for performance is batching,
我们可以将多个系统调用在单个事务中批量处理。
we can batch many system calls into a single transaction.
最后一个获得高性能的方法是并发。
And the final big idea for performance is concurrency.
这些是所有的事情，
And these are all the things,
ext3 做的，而 xv6 没有做的事情。
these are basically the things that ext3 does, that xv6 doesn't do.
好的，我将分别谈谈这三个高性能技术。
Okay, so I'm gonna talk about each one of these three performance techniques.
抱歉，我想问一下批处理的事，
Oh, sorry, I wanted to ask about batching,
我想 xv6 允许多个系统调用
I think xv6 allow for there to be multiple system calls
同时执行 start_op end_op ，
that do start_op end_op, like at kind of the same time,
然后它们一起提交。
so then they will commit together.
是的， xv6 是有限数量的批处理。
Yeah, that's true, xv6 is a limited amount of batching.
好的，谢谢。
Right, thank you.
好的，那么第一个，异步系统调用，
Okay, so first, asynchronous system calls,
这意味着系统调用返回，
this just means the system calls return,
但是它们修改了缓存中的块，然后返回，
but they were modified blocks in the cache then return,
没有触发磁盘写入。
don't particularly, don't trigger disk writes.
所以，这对系统调用快速返回是一个明显的优势。
So this has the obvious advantage of the system calls return quickly.
它也支持 IO 并发，
It also allows for IO concurrency,
即应用程序可以进行一些文件系统调用，
that is the application can make some file system system calls,
这意味着文件系统要做大量的磁盘写入，
that imply that the file system to do a bunch of disk operations, disk writes,
但是应用可以返回到计算
but the application can then return to computing
与文件系统执行写入并行，
at in parallel with the file system doing whatever the writes are
那些系统调用所需的写入，
that are required by those system calls,
这就是 IO 并发。
so this called IO concurrency.
如果没有异步系统调用，
And without asynchronous system calls,
就很难获得 IO 并发性，
it's hard to get IO concurrency,
很难在磁盘操作和应用程序计算之间重叠，
hard to get overlap between disk operations and application computing,
如果应用程序必须等待磁盘写入完成。
if the applications always have to wait for the disk writes to complete.
异步系统调用的另一个好处是，
The other thing that's nice about asynchronous system calls is that
它们使执行大量批处理变得更容易，
they allow, they make it easier to do large amounts of batching,
可以帮助批处理。
so there's help batching.
异步系统调用的缺点是，
The downside of asynchronous system calls is that,
这意味着因为系统调用返回，
it means that just because the system calls return,
并不意味着工作，
doesn't mean that the work that,
（并不意味着）系统调用应该做的工作已经完成，
that system call ought to have done, has actually been completed,
所以，如果你编写一个程序，
so for example if you write a program
它创建文件并写入一些数据，
that creates a file and write some data,
然后关闭该文件，
and then closes the file,
然后在控制台上打印完成给用户，
and then prints done on the console to the user,
然后你拔下电脑电源，
and then you pull out the power plug on your computer,
重新启动电脑，
have to restart the computer,
你的数据可能不在那里了，
your data may not be there,
即使所有系统调用都返回了，
even though all the system calls returned
即使程序说，
and even though the programs are just said
我调用了那些系统调用，而且它们返回了。
look, you know I called those system calls they return.
这意味着在一个异步系统调用的世界里，
And this means that in a world with asynchronous system calls,
应用程序必须写得更仔细，
applications have to be written more carefully,
如果它们关心自己在崩溃中的行为，
if they if they care about their behavior with respect to crashes,
这是一个很大的问题，
this is actually kind of a big deal in,
在 xv6 中，如果一个写入返回，
in xv6, if a write returned,
数据就在磁盘上，
the data was on the disk
并且在崩溃后还在那里，
and would be there after a crash,
在 ext3 中，如果写入返回，
in ext3, if a write returns,
你对崩溃后会发生什么一无所知，
just, you don't know anything about what will happen after a crash,
可能在那里，也可能不在那里。
may or may not be there.
所以，尽管异步系统调用可能编写谨慎的程序，
So it is possible despite asynchronous system calls to write careful programs,
比如数据库就需要小心，
like databases need to be careful,
文本编辑器需要小心，
text editors need to be careful,
如果我写一个文件，
if I write out a file,
我不想，
you know I do not want,
如果我在文本编辑器里写一个文件的时候停电了，
if there's a power failure while I'm writing out a file in my text editor,
我不想在启动之后看到乱码或部分文件，
that I don't want after be starting to see garbage or a partial file
我想看的是旧文件或新文件。
and I want to see either the old file or the new file.
所以文件系统还提供了一些用于谨慎应用的技术，
And so the file system also provides some techniques for careful applications,
在崩溃的情况下获得可预测的行为，
to get predictable behavior despite crashes,
主要工具是系统调用 fsync ，
and the main tool for that is called, system call called fsync,
所有 Unix 系统都有，
which you know all Unix systems have,
这里说的是，
and what this basically says is that
你向它传递一个文件描述符，
you pass it a file descriptor,
它告诉文件系统，执行所有写入，
and it tells the file system, look actually do all of the writes,
我可能调用了写入很多东西并调用 fsync ，
I may have called write a bunch of things and call fsync,
我现在想让你真正写入，
I now want you to actually do the writes
不要在写入到磁盘之前从系统调用返回，
and don't return from this system call until the writes are on disk
保证它们还在那里，如果发生崩溃。
and are guaranteed to be still there, if there's a crash.
所以，如果你查看数据库或文本编辑器的代码，
So if you look at the source code for databases or text editors,
还有其他关心它们数据的程序，
a number of other programs that really care about their data,
你会看到一些对 fsync 的调用，
you'll see sort of carefully place calls to fsync,
为了克服这个，
in order to sort of overcome this,
为了避免这些异步系统调用。
to fight that against these asynchronous system calls.
大多数程序，比如编译器，
Most programs are like your compiler,
这不是大问题，
it's no big deal,
如果发生崩溃，编译器的输出消失了，
if a the output of the compiler goes away, if there's a crash,
有很多很多程序，
there for many many programs,
不会调用 fsync ，
you know don't call fsync
很高兴得到异步系统调用的良好性能，
are very happy to get the good performance of asynchronous system calls
并不担心它们的崩溃行为。
and are not worried about their crash behavior.
好的，那么。
Okay, so.
这是不是有时也叫 flush ，
This, is this also called like flush sometimes,
因为我以前听过这个词。
because I think that that words, I've heard that word before.
是的，你可以，
Yeah, you could,
一种合理的解释 fsync 作用的方式是，
a reasonable way to explain what fsync does is that
它将这个文件的所有写入刷新到磁盘，
it flushes all previous writes to this file to the disk
并且返回，
and only returns that,
flush 是一个合理的词，
flush is a reasonable word for this,
flush 写入到磁盘中。
flush writes to disk.
好的，这就是异步系统调用。
Okay, so that's the asynchronous system calls.
ext3 使用的下一种技术是批处理。
The next technique the ext3 uses is batching.
这里的做法是，
And, the game here is that,
在任何时候，
there's at any one time,
ext3 中总是有一个打开的事务，
there's always one open transaction in the ex3 ext3,
ext3 中的事务可以
a transaction in ext3 can
保存许多不同系统调用的写入，
actually hold the writes of many different many distinct system calls,
所以 ext3 要做的是启动一个新事务，
so the what ext3 does is going to start a new transaction now
然后在接下来的几秒钟内，
and then for the next couple of seconds,
执行的所有系统调用都是，
all system calls that execute are,
它们的写入都是那个大事务的一部分，
their writes are part of that one big transaction,
我认为默认情况下，
I think by default,
ext3 只在每 5 秒创建一个新事务，
ext3 only creates a new transaction every five seconds,
所以每个事务可能有最多 5 秒的系统调用，
so each transaction may have up to five seconds worth of system calls in it,
所以作为一个大的批处理，
all as a huge batch,
然后在 5 秒钟结束时，
and then at the end of the five seconds,
ext3 提交这个单个的大事务，
ext3 will commit the single big transaction
可能包含上百个更新块，
that may have hundreds of updated blocks in it,
将这个事务作为单个事务提交。
commit this transaction to disk as a single transaction.
所以这个有优势的的原因，
And so the reason why this is a win,
首先，它分散了一些固定的事务成本，
first of all, it spreads some fixed transaction costs,
摊销了很多系统调用中固定的事务成本，
amortizes some fixed transaction costs across many system calls,
比如，你必须写入描述符块和提交块，
so, for example, you have to write the descriptor block and the commit block
你必须在机械驱动器上寻找，
and you have to seek on a mechanical drive,
至少你必须寻找，
at least you have to seek
让驱动器旋转到日志所在的位置，
and let the drive rotate to the place where the log is,
这些都是很大的开销，
and those are significant costs
而它们对于批处理只需要做一次，
and they only have to be done once for batch,
而不是每个系统调用一次。
instead of once per system call.
因此，它降低了这些成本的影响。
So, it lowers the impact of those those costs.
另一个大事是，
The other big deal is that,
另一个大事是它允许写入吸收，
another big deal is that it allows write absorption,
也就是说，
that is,
它是这种情况，
it's often the case,
你有一个完整的系统调用序列，
that you have a whole sequence of system calls,
一次又一次地修改完全相同的块，
that end up modifying the very same blocks over and over again,
比如，如果我创建了一大堆文件，
so for example if I create a whole bunch of files,
我需要分配一堆 inode ，
I need to allocate a bunch of inodes
所有的 inode 都很小，可能只有 64 个字节，
and that means all inodes are small, maybe 64 bytes,
这么多 inode 可以放在一个块中，
so many, many inodes fit in a block,
所以，连续创建一堆文件
so creating a bunch of files in a row
会使几个块中的许多 inode 变脏，
is gonna dirty many inodes in a few blocks,
因为有很多块的 inode 。
because there's many inodes for block.
类似地，如果我要将大量数据写入文件，
Similarly, if I'm writing a bunch of data to a file,
我可能需要分配很多数据块，
I may need to allocate a lot of data blocks,
我可能会翻转空闲位图中的许多位，
I may flip many of the bits in the block free map
如果我分配彼此相邻的块，
and if I allocate blocks that are next to each other,
它们的位将放在同一个块中，
their bits are going to be in the same block,
所以，我可能在一个块中放很多位，
and so I may put many bits in just one block,
所以，许多系统调用可能会一次又一次地操作相同的块。
so many system calls again may operating the same blocks over and over again.
在使用批处理的系统中，
And in the system with batching,
这些很多写入相同的数据块，
those many many writes the same blocks,
只是对缓存发生得非常快，
just happen very quickly to the cached,
只是数据块的缓存拷贝，
just the cache copies of blocks,
因为我们还没有写入磁盘，
because we're not writing the disk
然后，我们将这些少量数据块写入磁盘，
and then we write the those small number of blocks to the disk
只在事务结束时写入一次，
only once at the end of the transaction
而单个块写入日志，
and the single block write into the, on the writing of the log,
将许多修改的系统调用放入同一个块中。
reflects many many system calls with modifications to the same block.
所以，这种写入吸收可以减少总次数的数量，
So this write absorption could be
明显减少我们必须写入块的总次数，
reduce the amount of the total number times we have to write the block dramatically
与类似 xv6 的同步系统相比。
compared to a synchronous system, like xv6.
最后的重大优势是磁盘调度，
And the final big win is disk scheduling,
一般来说，即使我们，
in general, even if we are,
假设我们必须向磁盘写入一千个块，
suppose we have to write a thousand blocks to the disk,
它的效率要高得多，
it turns out to be much more efficient,
当然是在机械磁盘上，
certainly in mechanical drives,
但是即使在固态驱磁盘中，
but even in solid state drives,
为了在顺序位置中一次写入一千个块，
to write a thousand blocks all at once in sequential locations,
就像你对日志所做的那样，
as you would do to a log,
做这个要快的多，
as much faster to do that
跟写入一千个块每次都在不同的地方比较，
than to write a thousand blocks one at a time to different locations
甚至一千个块，
or even a thousand blocks,
甚至在日志中写入相同的块一千次。
you know even write the same block a thousand times in a log.
所以，通过让磁盘进行大批量写入，
So by handing up the disk large batches of writes to do,
这样可以更有效率，
this can be much more efficient,
我们不仅获得效率
there's also not only do we get an efficiency
从顺序写入日志中的很多块，
from writing a large number of blocks sequentially in the log,
但是即使我们要写入原位置，
but even when we go to write the home locations
为一批写入，
for this, for a batch of writes,
由单个大事务中的一批操作产生，
resulting from a batch of operations in a single big transaction,
如果我们可以向该驱动器大量的写入，
even then if we can hand a very large number of writes to that drive,
即使有不同的位置，
even if there are different locations,
因为有原位置，
because there to the home locations,
涉及多个不同的系统调用，
you know referred to by many different system calls,
如果我们允许磁盘调度大量不同的写入，
if we allow the disk to schedule a large number of distinct writes,
它可以选一个顺序把它们放进去，
it can pick an order to do them in,
这在机械磁盘上特别有效率，
that's particularly efficient on a mechanical drive,
这对它们进行排序，
this would done involve sorting them
按驱动器上的磁道号进行排序，
and sorting them by track number on the drive
从一个到另一个只需一次小的寻找，
and doing you know just a little seek from one to the next,
它们可以进行这种排序，
and they can do this sort,
如果你同时得到所有的块。
if you get all of the blocks at the same time.
即使是在固态硬盘上，
And but even on a solid state drive,
这里也有一些小优势，
it turns out there's a smaller win to be gotten
给磁盘大量的工作去做。
from giving the disk lots of work to do.
不管怎么说，你能得到这种磁盘调度，
Anyway, so this you can only really get this kind of disk scheduling,
如果你有非常大批量写入交给磁盘，
if you have very large batches of write to give to drive,
所以这是批处理的又一个优势。
so there's another win from batch.
好的，
Alright,
ext3 的最后一个重大优势是并发，
and, a final big win from the ext3 gets concurrency,
它有两种并发性，
it's really get two kinds of concurrency
与 xv6 比较。
that it benefits from compared to xv6.
一个是，它可以允许多个系统调用同时执行，
One is that, it can allow many system calls to execute at the same time,
所以，我们可以并行进行多个系统调用。
so we can have many individual system calls in parallel.
因为至少，
Because at least,
在 ext3 决定关闭并提交当前事务之前，
until ext3 decides to close out and commit the current transaction,
系统调用不必相互等待，
the system call don't have to wait for each other,
它们都可以修改属于当前事务的块，
they can all modify blocks that are part of the current transaction
并且所有这些系统调用都可以并行执行，
and all these many many system calls can execute in parallel
并向当前事务添加块，
and contribute blocks to the current transaction,
这在多核计算机上尤为重要，
that's particularly important on a multi-core machine,
在没有不同内核的地方，
where we don't want to have the different cores,
我们等待锁，
we're waiting for a lock,
在 xv6 经常是不允许的，
in xv6 we often, it's often the case that you're not allowed,
系统调用不能进行，
system call can't proceed,
因为当前事务正忙于做其他事情。
because the current transaction is busy doing something else.
在 ext3 中的大多数情况下，
Most of the time in ext3,
许多系统调用都可以修改当前事务。
many system calls can modify the current transaction.
ext3 获得并发性的另一种方式是
The other way that ext3 gets concurrency is that
可以有多个事务，
there can be multiple transactions,
处于不同执行阶段的旧事务。
older transactions in different stages of execution.
所以，只有一个打开的事务可以接收系统调用，
So it's true, system calls only the one open transaction can receive system calls,
但是其他正在向磁盘写入内容的事务可以并行进行，
but the other transactions that are writing things to disk can go on in parallel,
所以很多老的事务，
so many older transactions
在事务生命周期中的不同阶段，
and the different sort of stages in a transaction's life,
可以并行进行。
that can go on in parallel.
首先，这里有一个打开的事务，
First, there's the one open transaction,
可以有一些最近的事务，
there can be some number of transactions that are recent
文件系统正在提交它们，
and the file system is committing them,
但它们仍在将数据块写入磁盘，
but they're still writing their blocks to the disk,
所以，我们有一些事务正在提交到日志中。
so we have some number of transactions are currently committing to the log.
我们不用等这些结束，
And we don't have to wait for these to finish,
我们可以在新的打开事务中继续系统调用，
that is we can continue with system calls in the new open transaction,
虽然之前仍在写入日志的事务
while the previous transactions still writing to the log
还没有完成，仍在提交中。
hasn't actually finished, committing yet.
当然，这个阶段结束，
Of course, this stage ends,
当事务将提交块写入磁盘中的日志时。
when the transaction writes its commit block to the disk, the log.
可以存在事务，
There can be transactions,
甚至更旧的事务正在写入，
that are even older transactions that are writing,
它们的块缓存到原位置，
their blocks from the cache to the home locations,
修改后的数据块，
the modified blocks
最后，没有更多工作，
and finally this doesn't take much work,
那么最老的事务可以被释放。
but there can be, the oldest transactions are being freed.
这并不需要工作本身，
This doesn't really take work itself,
工作是，
the work is,
它在写事务到它们的原位置，
it's really writing transactions to their home, the blocks of their home locations,
不管怎样，通常存在多个事务，
but anyway, there's typically multiple transactions
存在于不同的阶段。
existence in these different stages.
所以，特别是，
And so in particular,
新的系统调用可以在不等待较旧事务的情况下执行，
new system calls can execute without waiting for older transactions
完成对日志的提交，
to either finish committing to the log
或完成写入它们的原位置，
or finish writing their blocks, their home locations,
与 xv6 不同的是，
in contrast to xv6,
新的系统调用必须等待所有完成，
where new system calls had to wait for this to complete for all,
对于之前的事务。
for the one previous transaction.
我有一个问题，
I have a quick question,
那么它是如何工作的，
so how does it work,
当有操作时，
when there's an operation
或者当有东西写入缓存块时，
or when something is writing to a cache block
而块也在被写入到磁盘中。
and the block is also being writing to the disk.
好的，所以这，
Okay, so there's,
这确实是个问题，
so that is indeed a problem,
而且，
and the,
这里有一个潜在的困难，
there's a potential difficulty here,
因为事务写入日志的内容
because a transaction you know stuff that a transaction writes to the log
应该仅包括由该事务中的系统调用进行的更新，
should only include updates made by a system calls that were in that transaction,
不应包括其他块更新，
shouldn't include any any block updates
由事务后的系统调用所做的，
made by system calls that came after that transaction,
因为如果你这样做了，
because if you did,
你可能会有提交的风险，
you risk sort of committing,
日志更新只表示了部分系统调用，
but having the log updates that only represent partial system calls,
因为我们希望确保
as we want to make sure
事务只包含所有给定的系统调用更新，
that a transaction only contains all of any given system calls updates,
所以，我们不能允许事务
so we can't afford to have a transaction
包含事务开始关闭后发生的任何更新，
include updates made by anything that happened after the transaction started to close
ext3 解决它的方法，
and the way ext3 deals with that,
至少在理论上，
is that at least notionally,
它制作一个副本，
it makes a copy,
当它决定结束当前打开的事务时，
when it decides to wrap up the current open transaction,
它会复制该事务的所有块，
it makes a copy of all the blocks for that transaction
直到它结束该事务为止。
as of the time it closed out this transaction.
所以它在某种程度上复制了所有的块，
So it sort of makes copies of all the blocks
然后，通过复制的块，
and then it's though that copy of the blocks
那个事务提交它的日志，
that the transaction commits into its log
任何较新的事务都有它们自己修改的块副本，
and any newer transactions have their own copy of that block that they modify,
与提交到日志的副本不同。
it's different copy from the moment committing to the log.
为了让这个更高效，
And in order to make this efficient,
系统使用了写入时复制方案，
the system actually uses a kind of copy-on-write scheme
避免复制，直到它注意到
to avoid making the copies until it actually notices
更新的事务需要写入那个块。
that a newer transaction needs to write that block.
酷，理解了。
Cool, that make sense.
好的。
Okay.
很好，并发可以提高性能的原因，
Good, and so the the reason why concurrency helps performance again
它可以帮助我们，
is that it can help us,
如果我们可以并行运行系统调用，
if we can run system calls in parallel,
我们得到了多核并行，
we get multi-core parallelism,
如果我们可以同时运行应用程序和系统调用，
and if we can run applications and system calls at the same time,
我们正在写入磁盘，
we're writing a disk,
我们可以获得 IO 并发性，
then we can get IO concurrency,
它可以在 CPU 之间重叠，
that is overlap between CPU,
CPU 执行和磁盘 IO 。
and CPU execution and disk IO.
所有这些帮助，
And all these sort of help,
更有效地利用硬件资源和使用机器。
use the hardware resources, the machine more efficiently, more intensively.
好的，有没有关于并发性的问题？
Alright, any questions about concurrency?
好的，我想让你感受一下
Alright, I want to just give you a taste of
实际的文件系统代码，
what the actual file system code,
如果你查看文件系统的 Linux 源码，
if you look at the Linux source for the file system,
从抽象的层次，
sort of somewhat abstract level,
这是每个系统调用的样子。
this is the way each system call looks.
你可能有 unlink 系统调用，
So you might have unlink system call,
这在 xv6 中非常熟悉，
and this is you know pretty familiar from xv6,
每个系统调用需要说，
we need to every system call needs to say,
这是写入序列的开始，
here's the beginning of the sequence of writes,
我即将执行一系列写入操作，
I'm about to do a sequence of writes
它们需要关于崩溃是原子的。
and they need to be atomic with respect to crash.
所以，任何系统调用，
So every system call,
on any transaction system,
必须有一个清晰的开头和结尾，
there has to be a clear sort of begin and end,
这两点之间的一切都需要是原子的。
everything between these two points needs to be atomic.
这里有一个名为 start 的系统调用，
And there's a start call the system call code makes,
事实证明，
and it turns out that,
ext3 必须知道处于活动状态的不同系统调用，
ext3 has to be aware of the different system calls that are active,
原因我会马上解释。
for reasons I'll explain that in a minute or two.
所以，每个系统调用，
So every system call,
当我调用 start 时，会得到一个所谓的句柄，
when I call start actually gets what's called a handle,
这是这个特定系统调用的唯一标识符，
this is a unique identifier of this particular system call,
它创建的写入是日志，
and the writes that it makes are logging,
文件系统用于跟踪，
the file systems sort of keep track of,
那个写入是由这个特定的系统调用完成的，
yeah that write was done by this particular system calls
然后系统调用这些读写块，
and then the system call these read and write blocks
所以它获得块，
and so it makes a get hold of a block,
或者一个块缓冲器缓存，
or really a buffer, a block cache buffer,
调用它，
makes it get call
它给出句柄，
and it tells the handle
然后是它需要读写的块。
and then the block number it needs to read or write.
然后它可能会执行大量这样的写入操作。
Then it may do a bunch of these write,
如果你需要修改很多块。
if you need to modify many blocks.
然后修改缓存中的块。
And then modifies, so then modify the blocks in the cache.
当它完成时，
And when it's done,
这个特定的系统调用完成时，
this, this particular system calls done,
它发出一个 stop 调用，
it makes a stop call,
并传递句柄给 stop 调用。
and pass the handle to stop call.
所以，这些是为了通知日志系统，
So, a lot of what this is about is informing the logging system,
一旦系统调用开始，
you know once a system call starts,
不允许提交事务，
a transaction is not allowed to commit
直到该事务中开始的所有系统调用都已完成。
until all the system calls that started in that transaction have finished.
因为它们是多个事务，
So and because they're gonna be multiple transactions,
系统必须能够联系，
the system has to be able to associate,
使用句柄的一个原因，
one of the reasons for the handles,
文件系统可以记得
so the system the file system can remember
对于每个系统调用是哪个事务的一部分。
for each system call which transaction it was part of.
所以它知道，哦，这个刚结束，
So it knows, oh and this just finishes,
这是特定事务等待的系统调用之一，
that's one of the system calls a particular transaction was waiting for,
在它可以提交之前。
before it could actually commit.
我们将句柄传递给 get 系统调用，
We pass the handle to the get system call,
每个事务都有一堆块，
so that every system every transaction has a bunch of blocks,
与作为该事务的一部分的被修改的块相关。
that are associated with with blocks modified as part of that transaction.
所以，我们在这里要说的，
So what we're saying here,
除了获得块的指针之外，
among as well as getting a pointer to the block
我们告诉日志系统，
is we're telling the logging system,
这个块编号是这个事务的一部分，
look, this block number is part of the transaction,
这个句柄所关联的（事务）。
that this handle refers to.
这个 stop 调用并不会调用提交，
This stop call doesn't actually calls a commit,
它只是告诉日志系统，
it just tells that logging system,
在这个事务中活动的系统调用减少了一个。
look, you know you have one fewer system calls that are active in this transaction.
所以，一个事务可以提交，
And so a transaction can only commit,
只有这个事务中启动的所有系统调用都调用了 stop 时，
if all of the system calls that started in this transaction have called stops,
事务必须做一些记录，
the transaction has to do some bookkeeping,
记住开始的所有句柄，
has remember all the handles that started,
这样，当它们调用 stop 时，可以进行检查。
so that it can sort of check them off as those calls finish.
所以考虑到这个结构，
So with this structure in mind,
我将展示完整的序列，
I'm just going to lay out the complete sequence
提交事务需要什么。
of what it takes to commit a transaction.
所以，在某个时候，当所有的，
So you know at some point when all the,
每隔 5 秒，文件系统会考虑，
every five seconds, the file system is going to think to itself,
哦，现在是提交当前打开的事务的好时机。
oh, now would be a good time to commit the current open transaction.
所以，这是会发生的事，
And so here's what happens when the,
当文件系统提交事务时。
here's what's involved in the file system committing a transaction.
所以，有这些步骤。
So, these are like steps.
所以，首先，我们必须阻塞所有新的系统调用，
So first, we have to block any new system calls,
我们需要让我们的事务只反映整个系统调用，
we need to have our transaction reflect only entire system calls,
所以我们不想让任何新的开始，
so we don't want to let anything new start,
当我们试图提交事务时，
when we're trying to commit the transaction,
我们希望只包括已经开始的系统调用，
we want to only include system calls that have already started,
所以你需要阻塞新的系统调用。
so you need to block new system calls.
还有另一个原因，我要谈一谈，
There's actually another reason, I'll talk about,
为什么我们需要阻塞新的系统调用。
why we need to block new system calls.
这是一个小的性能缺陷，
This is actually a little bit of a performance defect,
这里会有一段时间，
there's going to be a period of time here,
系统调用必须等待并且不允许执行，
when system calls have to wait and are not allowed to execute,
所以那太糟糕了。
so that's too bad.
第二步是，
The second step is that,
有一些已经启动的系统调用，
there are a bunch of system calls have already started
它们是该事务的一部分，
that are part of this transaction,
我们需要等它们完成，
that we need to wait for them to finish,
所以我们需要等待未完成的系统调用，
so we need to wait for the outstanding system calls,
它们在这个事务中。
that are in this transaction.
因为我们当然希望事务反映它们的所有写入，
Because of course we want the transaction to reflect all of their writes,
所以我们需要等它们完成。
so we need to wait for them to finish.
接下来发生的事情是，
The next thing that happens is
一旦该事务的所有系统调用都完成，
you know once all the system calls for this transaction are finished,
并且完成对缓存的写入，
and have done their writes into the cache,
就可以启动新事务，
it turns out then it's okay to start a new transaction
并让这些被阻塞的系统调用继续进行。
and let these blocked system calls continue.
所以现在我们要打开一个新的事务，
So now we're gonna open a new transaction
为任何后续的系统调，
for these, for any subsequent system calls,
但是现在，
but now this,
我继续我们最初的事务，
I'm continuing the story with our original transaction
它现在已经结束。
which is now closed.
所以记住 ext3 中的日志
So remember the log in ext3
包含描述符、数据块和提交块。
contains descriptors and data blocks and commit blocks.
现在，我们知道修改的全部数据块，
So now, we know the full set of blocks modified
这个事务中的所有系统调用（所修改的），
by all the system calls that were in this transaction,
因为它们都使用一个句柄调用了 get ，
because they all called get with a handle,
告诉我们是哪个事务的一部分，
that told us about what transactions are part of,
我们知道该事务的全部修改块，
we know the full set of modified blocks for this transaction,
所以现在我们可以写一个描述符块，
so now we can write a descriptor block,
有所有块编号，
that has all the block numbers
对于这个事务的的所有脏块。
for all the blocks dirty to this transaction.
我们还将写入修改的块，
We're also going to write the actual modified blocks
从磁盘缓存到日志中，
from the disk cache into the log
事实上，如果有人问一个问题，
and in fact if somebody somebody asks a question about,
如果下一个事务修改了这个会发生什么，
oh, what happens if the next transaction modifies this,
我们在这个阶段实际写入的是
what we're actually writing in this stage is
这个事务块保存的副本，
the sort of saved copies of this transactions blocks
在它完成时。
as of the time when it finished.
所以，我要把块写入日志。
So I'm gonna write the actual blocks to the log.
现在，我们要等这些写入结束，
Now, we're gonna wait for these writes to finish,
这些需要完成，然后我们才能继续。
these need to finish before we can proceed.
一旦确保描述符和数据块在磁盘上，
Once the descriptor and the data blocks are guaranteed to be on the disk,
然后，我们可以将提交记录写入日志。
then we can write the commit record to the log.
一旦写入完成，我们就必须等待它完成。
And once that write is finished, we have to wait for it to finish.
所以我们在等待提交写入完成，
So we're waiting for the waiting for the commit write to finish,
一旦提交写入完成，
at this point, once the commit write is finished,
这个事务，
this transaction,
用技术术语来说，
with the sort of technical term is
就是这个事务达到了提交点，
that this transaction has reached its commit point that is,
在这一点上保证写入和事务在崩溃中幸存下来，
it's guaranteed the writes and transaction are guaranteed to survive a crash at this point,
如果崩溃发生在写提交块之前，
if the crash had occurred before this before writing the commit block,
事务的写入不会出现在崩溃并重启之后，
the writes of the transaction would not appear after a crash and reboot
并运行恢复软件，
and running the recovery software,
如果崩溃现在发生，
if a crash occurs now,
在提交块已经写入磁盘之后，
after the commit point after the commit block has written to the disk,
然后可以保证
then they're guaranteed to
保证事务中的所有写入
those writes all the writes in the transaction are guaranteed
在崩溃、重启和恢复之后出现。
to appear after crash reboot and recovery.
好的，现在，
Okay, and now and only now,
所有这些事情都是在幕后发生的，
in the background, all this kind of happened in the background,
没有进程在等待这些东西，
no process was really waiting for this stuff,
现在，我们可以将事务块写入
now we can write the transactions blocks
它们在文件系统中的原位置。
to their home locations in the file system.
我将在几分钟后讨论，
And, I ll talk about in a few minutes
在这些写入都完成后，
after all of these writes have completed,
作为该事务一部分的所有块，
for all the blocks that are part of this transaction,
只有那时，我们才能重用那部分日志。
then only then can we reuse that part of the log.
所以在一个非常繁忙的系统中，
So in a very busy system,
如果日志头赶上了尾，
if the head of the log catches up with the tail,
可能无法启动新事务，
there may actually may not be able to start a new transaction
直到最旧的事务的所有这些写入完成，
until all of these writes have finished for the oldest transaction,
因为我们可能需要日志空间，
because we may need log space,
所以我们不会，
so we won't,
我们可能需要重用最旧的事务日志空间，
we may need to reuse the oldest transaction log space,
我们必须进行写入
we have to write for it to
写入所有缓存块到它们的原位置，
write all the cache cache blocks to their home locations,
通常人们尽量把日志做得足够大，
this usually you people try to make the log big enough,
这种情况很少发生，
this happens pretty rarely,
所以，这些东西可以在后台进行。
so that this stuff can go on in the background.
任何关于这些步骤，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about these steps?
哦，抱歉，那些东西在哪里运行？
Oh, sorry, where are those run?
它们什么？
Those what?
我们写入这些文件系统的东西。
We write for doing this file system stuff.
哦，你说没有程序等着这些事情做完，
Oh, so you said that no process is waiting for those things to get done,
那么它们在哪里运行？
so where, where are they scheduled where they run?
哦，有一个后台线程，
Oh, there's a background thread,
在内核中专门有一个后台线程。
there's a background thread, in the kernel dedicated.
我明白了，谢谢。
I see thank you.
我有关于重用部分日志的问题，
I have question actually about reusing part of the log,
所以，让我们，
so let's,
比如，最终我们开始使用日志的特定部分，
let's say eventually we start using a particular section of log,
而日志那个特定的部分，
and log, the that particular, as I think just mentioned,
日志的特定部分，
that particular log of particular part of the log
在我的新事务中，
actually in my new transaction,
最终使用刚刚被释放的日志部分，
actually, end up using the whole log part was just freed up
没有其他的了，
and there's nothing else,
没有空间给日志了，
there's no more space for the log,
然后系统只是等待，
what the log, then like with the system just wait
直到日志的另一部分被释放，
until the another portion of log is freed up,
或者它会做一些其他事情？
or would it do something else too?
是的，它会等待，
Yes, it'll wait,
让我来画一张图，
let me though, let me just draw a picture
确定我回答的问题是对的。
to help me make sure I'm answering the right question here.
我们可以把日志看作是这条线，
We can think of the log as just this linear,
是磁盘的一部分，
part of the disk
在任何给定的时间，
and any given time,
也许最老的有效事务是 t7 ，
you know maybe maybe the oldest valid transaction is you know t7,
然后这个地区有 t8 ，
then there's t8 in this region
然后我们有 t9 ，
and we have t9
我们想要开始，
and we want to start,
我们想把 t10 放在这里。
you know, we want to put t10 here.
这个。
The.
让我们看看，
Let's see,
首先，我们想开始一个新的事务，把它放在这里。
what one you know we'd like to start a new transaction put it here.
我们可能要等待 t7
The, we may have to wait for t7
把它的所有块写到原位置上，
to write all it's blocks to their home locations,
这样我们才能释放它。
so that we can free it.
这可能意味着事务 10 中的东西不得不暂停，
And that may mean that the transaction stuff in transaction 10 may have to pause,
等待日志中的这些空间释放。
waiting for this space in the log to free up.
这是你说的吗？
Is that what you're talking about?
是的，这么说吧，
Yeah, so let's say that,
所以一开始可能是这种情况，
so it could be the case at the beginning,
我可以把事务 10 的块放在可用空间中，
you I can put in blocks for a transaction 10 in the actual free space right now,
但是最终，如果日志变得足够大，
but eventually, if log grows big enough,
它就会耗尽空闲空间，
it's just going to run out of free space
在这一点上，
and at that point,
它需要等待事务 7 。
it's just going to wait for transaction 7 to.
是的。
Yes.
被记录下来，好的。
Be recorded, okay.
是的，是的，如果有足够的活动进行，
Yes, yes, certainly if there's enough activity going on
而日志绕回得足够快，
and the log wraps around quickly enough,
你可能不得不等待新的新系统调用，
you may end up having to wait for a new new system calls,
我们甚至可能无法启动系统调用，
we may not even be able to start the system calls,
在我们释放日志中的空间之前，
because before we can free up space in the log
为它们修改的块。
for the blocks that they're going to modify.
如果你关心这件事的细节，
And you know if you care about the details of this
就会发现这里有死锁的可能，
it turns out there's some potential deadlocks here,
意思是 ext3 最终，
that require that mean ext3 ends up,
系统调用必须预先声明它们将需要多少块，
system calls have to pre declare how many blocks they're going to need,
这样日志系统能知道需要多少，
so that the logging system knows how much,
你可以推论这个事务是否有足够的空间，
you can reason about whether or there's enough space for this transaction,
因为我们不想让事务开始，
because we don't want to allow a transaction to start that,
我们不能提交到日志中。
we wouldn't actually be able to commit into the log.
好的。
Okay.
假设，
Let's, let's say,
你试图放入的新日志或新事务，
it's the new log or the new transaction you're trying to put,
要到事务 8 ，
goes to like 8 transaction 8,
所以你必须等待 7 和 8 ，对吧，
so you will have to wait for 7 and 8 right,
那么这是怎么运作的？
so how does that work?
你的意思是，
You mean,
好的，
okay so,
事务 7 ，事务 8 和事务 9 ，
it's transaction 7 and transaction 8 transaction 9,
至少在这张图中的都必须完成，
at least in this diagram have all completed
或者所有系统调用都已完成。
or that all the system calls have finished.
这些事务在日志中提交，
And these transactions are committed in the log,
因为这些是旧事务。
because these are the old transactions.
所以，在这张图中，
So, in this picture,
我们刚开始事务 10 ，
at least we're just starting transaction 10,
所以，新的系统调用将写入事务 10 。
and so new system calls are going to be writing into a transaction 10.
是的，但是你说过，
Right, but you said that,
事务 10 太大不能放入那个空间，
transaction 10 is not big enough to fill that space,
所以你需要释放事务 7 ，
so you need to free transactions 7 right,
你需要等待它提交到磁盘中。
you need to wait for that to like commit to disk.
是的。
Yes.
但是，会发生什么，
But what happens if you,
如果事务 10 比事务 7 大，
if it's, if 10 is like bigger than like 7,
它要到事务 8 。
like it goes to 8 transaction.
我们必须等待，
We have to wait for to,
是的，我们必须等待，
yeah, we may have to wait for,
不管事务 10 有多大，
however big transaction 10 is,
我们需要足够的磁盘空间来容纳它，
you know we need, we need enough space on the disk to fit it
而不是足够的日志来容纳它，
and not enough space in the log to fit it
所以，如果事务 10 很大，
and so indeed if transaction 10 and it turns out being big,
它可能需要强制多个事务，
it may need to force multiple transactions,
多个最旧事务写入它们的原位置，
multiple of the oldest transactions to write to their home locations
并释放它们自己。
and free themselves.
我猜它的代码是怎么工作的，
I guess how, how does code for that work,
比如，它是不是查看它有多大，
like does it just run through how big it is
这里有一个事务，这里也有一个事务，
and like say hey there's a transaction here and a transaction here
我必须等待它们两个。
and it's like I have to wait for both of them.
文件系统知道日志中的所有事务有多大，
The file system knows, knows how big all the transactions in the log are,
它记得，
and it remembers
记得我的意思是文件系统记得
and remember I mean actually the file system remembers
相当多关于每个较旧事务的信息，
quite a bit about each of these older transactions,
它知道每一个都是不是可写，
it knows for each one whether it's written,
文件系统跟踪所有这些块
for file system keeps track of for every block
在每个旧事务中的（块），
in all of each of these older transactions
它是否已经把那个块写到原位置，
whether it has written that block to the home location,
这样它就可以知道，
so that it can know,
哦，我已经写好了，它可以知道是不是。
oh, I've written, it could know whether or not.
并识别完成点，
And recognize the point at which is finished
写入所有事务 7 的块或事务 8 的块。
writing all the transactions 7 blocks or transactions 8 blocks.
所以这里有相当多的记录，
So there's quite a lot of bookkeeping going on here,
帮助文件系统了解每个旧事务的状态。
help the file system to understand in detail the state of every old transaction.
好的。
Okay.
好的，那么，
Okay, so,
这是关于如何重用日志空间的主题，
indeed there's there's on the topic of how to reuse log space,
这里有一个小细节需要说。
there's one little detail here that needs to be said.
如果你记得，一开始的时候。
If you remember, at the beginning of the.
让我来写一下图表，
Let me, let me writing diagram,
是一个超级块，
is actually a super block though,
日志超级块在日志的开头。
log super block at the beginning of the log.
所以在任何给定的时间里，
And so in any given time,
你可能会有日志超级块，
you might have the log super block,
然后是一些事务，
and then some set of transactions,
可能事务 4 是最新的事务，
you know, maybe those transaction 4 which is the newest transaction
然后是事务 1 ，较旧的事务，
and then a transaction 1, the older transactions,
这意味着，
so what this means is that,
当然，日志是环绕在一起的。
of course the log is wrapped around.
你知道，
And you know the,
我们是否可以重复使用一部分日志的规则，
yeah, the rule for whether we could reuse a part of the log,
我已经提到了，再说一遍，
now I've mentioned this before I just want to say it again
我们可以重用日志，
is that we can reuse the log,
我们就可以重用日志中事务 2 的这一部分，
so we can reuse this part of the log that transaction 2 is in,
如果 t2 已经提交，
if t2 has committed
并且所有 t2 的块已写入它们在文件系统中的原位置，
and all of t2 blocks have been written to their home locations in the file system,
这样在崩溃之后就不需要重播这些块了。
so that there can never be any need after a crash replay these blocks, right.
并且如果在事务 2 之前的所有事务也被释放。
And if all transactions prior to transaction 2 have also been freed.
如果这些条件都是真的，
So if those conditions are all true,
然后我们可以释放并重用 t2 所在的那部分日志，
then we can free and reuse the part of the log that t2 sits in,
所以我们能使用 t2 ，
so we can only use t2
在 t2 t1 完成提交之后，
and after t2 is, after t1 is finished all committing
并且写入日志块到原位置中，
and writing its blocks to log to the home locations also,
然后这个超级块，
and then this super block,
为了方便崩溃后的恢复软件，
for the convenience of the recovery software after a crash,
如果我们决定我们可以，
if we decide that we can,
如果文件系统决定
if the file system decides
它可以释放和重用日志的特定部分，
it can free and reuse a particular part of the log,
它也重写超级块，
it rewrites the super block too,
超级块作为第一个事务日志的指针，
super block as a pointer to the begin the first transaction log
所以，作为释放部分日志的一部分，
and so as part of freeing part of the log,
文件系统修改超级块指向
file system modifies super block point to
日志中当前最旧事务的开始。
the new beginning of the of the now oldest transaction in the log.
然后发生崩溃，
And then there's crash,
恢复软件读取超级块，找到开始的日志。
at the recovery software reads the super block, finds the beginning log.
好的，如果发生崩溃，
Okay, so if there's a crash,
当然崩溃导致 RAM 中的所有东西都消失了，
of course a crash causes everything in RAM to evaporate,
所以，所有记录，
so all that bookkeeping
文件系统记录着哪些块已写入原位置，
that the file system is keeping about what blocks have been written to the home locations,
如果发生崩溃或停电，这些都会丢失，
that's all lost if there's a crash or power failure,
然而，其中一个假设是
however so that one of the assumptions is
RAM 中没有任何有用的东西，
there's nothing useful in RAM,
在崩溃过程中唯一能保存下来的东西是
the only stuff that's can be preserved across the crash is
磁盘上的任何东西，
whatever's on the disk,
我们参与了所有这些关于日志的讨论，
but we are absolutely in all these discussions about logging,
假设盘完全完好无损，
assuming that the disk is completely intact,
磁盘没有任何问题。
that nothing went wrong with the disk.
所以，也许你们应该考虑的正确模型是，
So, so maybe the right model for you to think
出现电源故障，
in terms of is that there was a power failure,
所有的东西都在嗡嗡作响，然后停电了，
that everything was humming along and then the power failed,
系统在某个点上停止了，
the system just stopped at some point
在电源恢复后，
and the disk is after power is restored,
这上面有所有东西，
this just has whatever it had on it,
在断电时的（东西）。
at the point of the power failure.
所以我们绝对不会考虑
So we're absolutely not considering situations
磁盘不知何故被崩溃损坏或损坏。
in which the disk was somehow corrupted or destroyed by the crash.
所以崩溃当然可能会中断，
And so the crash of course may interrupt,
是的，事务正在提交或还没有提交，
yeah whatever transactions were in the middle of committing are not yet committing yet
或者不管崩溃打断什么，
or whatever the crash may interrupt,
无论是事务的提交
either the commit of a transaction
或者写入事务块到它们的原位置。
or the writing of a transactions blocks into their home locations.
所以，这意味着磁盘上的日志，
So, what that means is that the on disk log,
当电力恢复，回复运转时，
when the power is restored and recovery sufferers run,
它会有一堆旧的完整的事务，
it's going to have a bunch of complete transactions, older complete transactions,
可能是 t1 和 t2 。
you know may be t1 and t2.
让我举一个新的例子，用于恢复。
Let me take a new example, for for recovery.
比如我们有一个超级块，
Let's say we have the again the super block,
而且，也许在崩溃的时候，
and, maybe at the time of the crash,
最老的事务是 t6 ，
the oldest transaction was t6
然后是 t7 ，
and then there's t7,
然后我们绕回来，还在崩溃之前 t8 ，
then we wrapped around still before the crash t8
而且这里曾经有一个 t5 ，
and there was a t5,
但是 t8 已经已经重写了 t5 的第一部分，
but t8 has, let us imagine has started has overwritten the first part of t5,
因为我们知道 t5 在崩溃之前已经释放了，
because t5 was, we know that t5 was freed before the crash,
但是恢复软件不一定知道这一点。
but the recovery software doesn't necessarily know that.
假设超级块指向 t6 ，
And let's say the super block points to t6
作为最老的有效事务的开始，
as being the start of the oldest valid transaction,
t5 已经释放。
t5 is free.
我们要重新启动，
We're going to reboot with an [attack] disk,
恢复软件读取超级块，
the recovery software reads the super block
然后，它知道日志的开始位置，
and so then it knows the where the beginning of the log is,
然后恢复软件将在日志中向前扫描，
then the recover software's going to scan forward in the log
试图找到日志的末尾。
to try to find the end of the log.
我们需要找到解决问题的方法，
We need to have a way for it,
真正弄清楚日志的末尾，
to actually figure out, oh you know that's the end of the log,
它做到这一点的方法是，
the way it does that is
我们知道每个事务都包含一个描述符块，
we know that every transaction consists of a descriptor block
它指示事务上有多少数据块，
that indicates how many data blocks are on the transaction,
比如描述符块说有 17 个数据块，
such as descriptor blocks says, oh yeah there's 17 data blocks
我们预计会有 17 个数据块最终提交记录。
and we expect 17 data blocks and finally commit record.
然后是另一个描述符记录，
And then another descriptor record
然后描述符块包含的数据块的数量，
and then the number of data blocks implied by the descriptor block
然后是另一个提交块。
and then another commit block.
所以，正向扫描中的日志软件，
And so the log software in the scan forward,
可能 t6 和 t7 都没问题，
maybe t6 and t7 are fine,
然后它看一下 t8 ， t8 有一些描述符块。
then it's going to look at t8 t8 got some descriptor block.
然后，恢复软件查找
And, then the recovery suffers gonna look forward to
事务的结尾在哪里，
where the end of transaction it should be
并寻找一个提交块。
and look for a commit block.
所以这里可能发生几件事，
And so there's a couple of things that may have happened here,
可能是事务确实提交了，
it could be that transaction it did commit
恢复软件找到提交块，
and that the recovery software finds the commit block,
然后它会寻找另一个，
it'll then look for another,
它不知道事务是最后一个事务，
you know it doesn't know that transaction is last transactions
需要找出这一点，
needs to figure that out,
所以，它查找接下来的一个块，
so it's going to look at the very next block
查看这是否是有效的描述符块，
to see if this is a valid descriptor block,
我们知道这个块只是一个随机的块，
now we know that this block was really just a random block
在事务 5 中，
in the middle of transaction 5
完全不是描述符块，
and not a descriptor block at all,
那么问题是
then the question is
恢复软件如何能够可靠地区分，
how can the recovery software reliably distinguish between,
这是一个数据块，
oh, this is a, just some data block
在旧事务中间，
in the middle of an old transaction
或者是事务 9 的描述符块。
or it's the maybe the descriptor block for transaction nine.
有人知道有什么可靠的方法，可以做到这个吗？
Any guesses for a reliable method to do that?
是魔术数吗？
Is that the magic number.
是的。
Yeah.
还是有一个保留位。
Or is there just a reserved bit.
的确，
There is indeed,
每个描述符提交块都以某个魔术数开头，
every descriptor commit block starts with some magic number,
只是一个 32 位的值，
just just a 32 bit value,
这是恢复软件寻找的，
that the recovery software is looking for,
我其实不知道是什么。
I don't actually know what it is.
所以，游戏肯定是
So, definitely the game is
我们到了事务 8 的末尾，
that we come to the end of transaction 8,
如果下一个块以魔术数开头，
if the very next block starts with the magic number,
然后恢复软件会假设，
then the recovery software's gonna assume that,
哦，这是一个有效的描述符块。
oh this is a valid descriptor block.
你能不能，抱歉，有个问题，
Could you, sorry, quick question,
它是不是不可靠的，
would it be unreliable
它理解为一个描述符块，
to try to like, interpret it as a descriptor block,
尝试读取指定它们的数据块的数量，
try to read the number of data blocks that specifies them,
比如，查看是否在指定的位置有提交块，
like see if there's a commit block at the expected location
在一定数量的块之后。
after the number of blocks.
当然，如果这个日志看起来像一个描述符块，
Well, certainly if this log does look like a descriptor block,
那么它会继续，
then it will skip forward
并尝试读取对应的提交块，
and try to read the corresponding commit block,
如果提交块看起来不是提交块，
and if that commit block doesn't look like a commit block
有正确魔术数，
with the right magic number,
它不会认为在这个事务中。
it will not believe in this transaction.
这里剩下的一点细节就是，
The the the the the thing that's one little remaining detail here is that,
我们查找的块，
this block that we're looking at here and we're wondering
或者恢复软件怀疑的，
or the recovery software wondering,
这是否是描述符块，
if it's a descriptor block,
这可以是事务 5 中间的块，
this could be just a block right in the middle of transaction 5
包含任意位模式，
containing any arbitrary bit pattern,
它可能就是文件中的数据块，
it could be just like the data block from a file,
恰好是从这个神奇的数字开始的。
that just happens to begin with the magic number.
所以，作为最后的细节，
So you know as a final detail,
日志记录系统需要能够区分
the logging system needs to be able to distinguish
以魔术数开头的有效描述符块，
between a valid descriptor block that starts with this magic number
还是一些以魔术数开头的数据块。
and just some data block that starts with the magic number.
你可以想象不同的方式来做到这一点，
And you can imagine various ways of doing that,
在 ext3 所做的是，
in fact, what ext3 does is,
当它要向日志中写入块时，
whenever it's going to write a block to the log,
这不是一个描述符块或提交块，
that's not a descriptor block or commit block,
如果块以魔术数开头，它将其替换为零，
if that block starts with the magic number, it replaces that with zero
并在该事务描述符块中设置与该块对应的位，
and sets a bit corresponding to that block in that transaction descriptor block,
这个位意味着这个特殊的数据块
then that bit means this particular data block
以魔术数开始，我们用零代替它。
started with the magic number and we replace it with zero.
如果恢复软件需要重放那个块，
And then if the recovery software ever needs to replay that block,
我们假设事务 8 有一个这样的块，
so let's say transaction 8 had one of these blocks,
它最初是以魔术数开始的，
that originally started with the magic number,
它将设置这个魔术标志位，
it's going to set the bit this magic flag,
对应描述符块替换魔术数为零，
corresponding that block and the descriptor block and replace magic number was zero,
如果恢复重放这个块，
if recovery has to replay this block,
它将看到这个标志，
it'll see that flag
在将这个块重放到原位置之前，
and before replaying this block to its home location
使用魔术数替换零。
will replace the zero with the magic number.
所以，除了描述符或提交块之外，
And therefore, no block other than a descriptor or commit block
没有任何块可能以魔术数开头，
can possibly start with a magic number,
在这个记录系统中。
in this logging system.
所以我们从来没有模棱两可，
So we never have this ambiguity,
如果块在提交块之后，并以一个魔术数开头，
if the block after a commit block, starts with a magic number,
那么它一定是一个描述符块。
then it must be a descriptor block.
好的，
Okay, alright,
我们在做恢复，
so recovery, we were doing recovery,
它从块开始，
it starts at the block,
从超级块表示最老的事务的块向前扫描，
that the super block says is the beginning of the oldest transaction scans forward,
它向前扫描，直到，
and it'll scan forward until you, you know it,
查找描述符或其对应的提交块，
look at the descriptor or is their corresponding commit block
它停止在，
and it'll stop as soon as it sees
后面的是提交块，而不是描述符块，
oh the log following a commit block, wasn't a descriptor block at all,
或者，在提交块之后的块是一个描述符块，
or yeah the block following a commit block is a descriptor block,
但是应该有对应的提交块，
but the what should have been the corresponding commit block,
是有效的提交块，没有魔术数。
is now in fact a valid commit block, doesn't have the magic number.
所以在这一点上它会停止，
So at that point it will stop,
恢复软件清除日志到结尾，
recovery software will clear the log to the ended,
在最后一个有效提交块的地方。
at the point where the last valid commit block.
我们会忽略，
And we'll ignore,
这之后可能会有部分事务，
there may be a partial transaction after this,
开始提交，但没有结束，
that started to commit but didn't finish,
但是恢复软件忽略那部分事务，
but the recovery software ignores that partial transaction,
因为它没有所有的写入，
because it doesn't have all the writes,
所以不能自动恢复它，
so it can't restore it atomically,
然后恢复软件将返回到日志的开头，
and then the recovery software will go through go back to the beginning of the log
重放每个块，将每个块重写到其原位置，
and replay each block, rewrite each block to its home location,
一直贯穿日志，
all through the log,
到最后最后一个有效的提交块。
to the last, up to the last valid commit block.
然后它可以重启剩下的操作系统，
And then it can restart the rest of the operating system,
启动剩下的操作系统和可以运行的普通程序，
start the rest of the operating system and ordinary programs can run,
在恢复完成之前，你不能运行任何程序，
before recovery finishes, you can't you can't run any programs,
因为文件系统无效。
because the file system isn't valid.
关于恢复，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about recovery?
我有一个简短的问题，
I I have a quick question,
我想以前提到过这一点，
I think you mentioned this before,
但是在 xv6 中缺少这个日志事务方案的哪些部分呢？
but what parts of this logging transaction scheme is missing in xv6?
在 xv6 中缺少的主要功能是
The main thing, it's missing in xv6 is
在日志中有多个事务的能力，
the ability to have multiple transactions in the log,
在 xv6 中，日志最多只有一个事务，
so xv6 there's only ever at most one transaction in the log
所以你不能在 xv6 中得到这个并发性，
and so you you can't you don't get this concurrency in xv6,
当我执行来自事务 7 的系统调用时，
where while I'm executing system calls from transaction 7,
这将并行进入事务 7 ，
you know that are going to go into transaction 7,
同时， ext3 可以将事务 6 提交到磁盘。
in parallel, with that ext3 can be committing transactions 6 to the disk.
这个并发性在 xv6 中是不可用的，
That's not available of concurrency, is not possible in ext-, in xv6,
因为日志只保存一个事务，
because the the log holds just one transaction,
所以我们必须完成一个事务的所有工作，
so we have to completely do all the work for one transaction,
在我们允许开始下一个事务之前。
before we're allowed to start anything with the next transaction.
所以它是正确而简单的，
So it's correct and simple,
但是你不会从 xv6 中获得太多的并行性。
but you don't get a lot of parallelism out of xv6.
好的，谢谢,
Okay, thank you,
你是说，
are you saying that,
它仍然可以有多个事务块，
it can still have multiple transaction blocks,
但是它不能异步执行它们，
but it just can't execute them asynchronously,
对吗？
would that be correct?
xv6 ？
xv6?
xv6 。
xv6.
是的，它只有，
Yeah, it, it only has the,
一旦它决定，
once it decides to,
我的意思是图片有点混乱，
I mean the picture a little bit confused,
因为 xv6 可以允许一个以上的系统调用进入单个事务，
because xv6 can allow more than one system call into a single transaction,
所以 xv6 确实有一些并发性，
so xv6 does have some of this concurrency in it,
还有一些批处理，
and some of this batching,
但是一旦 xv6 决定开始提交事务，
but once xv6 decides to start committing a transaction,
它必须完全完成那个事务，
it has to completely finish with that transaction,
提交到磁盘，
committed to disk,
写入块到原位置，
you know write the header block write the blocks to the home locations
然后从日志中擦除该事务，
and then erase the transaction from the log,
它必须完成所有这些事情，
it has to do all that stuff,
在执行任何新的系统调用之前。
before it can execute any new system calls.
因为没有什么地方
Because there's nowhere you know there's nowhere
可以放置新系统调用的修改，
to put the modifications for the new system calls
直到前一事务完全完成，
until the previous transaction is completely finished,
所以， xv6 之间的某种交替，
so xv6 sort of alternates,
可以运行几个系统调用，然后提交事务，
between it can run a few system calls and then commit the transaction,
然后再运行几个系统调用，
and then run a few more system calls,
但是它不能重叠这两个。
but it can't serve overlap those two.
好的。
Alright.
ext3 可以。
ext3 can.
谢谢。
Thank you.
好的，这是 ext3 设计中相对简单的部分，
Okay, so that was a relatively straightforward part of ext3 design,
它还有一堆棘手的细节，
it turns out there's also a bunch of a tricky details,
其中有几点我想谈谈。
a few of which I want to talk about.
我之前提到过，有一个打开的事务，
So I mentioned before, that you know there's an open transaction,
但是当 ext3 决定想要关闭打开的事务时，
but when ext3 decides that it wants to close the open transaction,
它必须等待所有系统调用完成，
it has to wait for all system calls that transaction to finish
在任何新的事务可以开始前，
before it, any trans-, any new transactions are allowed to start,
所以可能有这样一张图片，
so that maybe a picture for that is that,
我们有原始的旧事务 t1 ，
you know we had original old transaction t1,
在事务 1 中执行多个系统调用，
then there were multiple system calls executing in transaction 1,
如果我们想要关闭事务 1 ，
if we want to close transaction 1,
我们必须停止接受新的系统调用，
we have to stop accepting new system calls,
因为我们想等现有的调用完成后才能提交，
because we want to wait for the existing ones to finish before we can commit,
但在所有这些系统调用完成之前，
but until these all these system calls finished,
在ext3 中不允许启动新的系统调用。
no new system calls are allowed to start in ext3.
所以如果这里有事务 2 ，
So if there's some transaction 2 here,
在事务 2 中不允许发生任何事情，
nothing is allowed to happen in transaction 2,
任何事情都不允许，
nothing allows to,
系统调用允许开始，直到这些系统调用已经完成，
system calls are allowed to start until these system calls have finished,
并且只有在那时，事务 2 才能开始接受系统调用。
and only then can transaction 2 start accepting system calls.
所以，这里有一段时间，
So, there's a period of time here,
其中新的系统调用都被阻塞，
in which new system calls are all blocked,
这降低了性能，
that reduces performance,
因为它可以执行系统调用，
because it could have been executing system calls,
但我们不允许这样做，
but we're not allowed to,
那么问题是，
then the question is,
为什么 ext3 不允许在事务 2 中启动新的系统调用，
how come ext3 doesn't allow new system calls to start in transaction 2,
直到事务 1 中的所有系统调用都完成。
until all system calls in transaction finished.
这是一个好问题，因为它限制了性能，
And you know it's a good question, because it limits performance,
让我给你们举个例子，
so let me give you an example,
如果 ext3 没有做到这一点，
if if the ext3 didn't do this,
那么可能会出现以下糟糕的情况。
then the following bad situation could arise.
那么，让我们假设事务 1 说其中有一个系统调用，
So let's suppose transaction 1 says one system call in it,
它是 create ，创建文件的系统调用，
and it's a create, a system call the create file,
可能是一个名为 x 的文件，
maybe a file called x
想法是，在这个 create 完成之前，
and the idea is that before this create is finished,
文件系统决定要启动一个新事务，
the file system decides it wants to start a new transaction,
打开一个新事务，
open up a new transaction
并且它将在 create 之后接受任何系统调用，
and it's going to accept any system calls after the create
在这个新的事务 t2 中，
in in this new transaction, transaction t2
事务 t2 开始，在 t1 结束之前，
is going to say t2 starts, before t1 finishes,
我们现在开始执行事务 2 中的系统调用，
and we start executing system calls now in transaction 2,
可能事务 t2 在某个其他文件上调用 unlink ，
maybe transaction t2 calls unlink on some other file,
那么 unlink 将释放与 y 相关联的 inode ，
well then unlink will free the inode associated with y, right,
所以可能，
and so maybe maybe,
在图中，我的时间是这个方向。
I'm having time go this way in my diagram.
可能在这个时间点，事务 2 标记 inode 空闲，
Maybe at this point in time transaction 2 marks the inode is free,
标记 y 的 inode 空闲，
marks the inode for y is free,
create 当然必须为 x 分配 inode ，
create of course has to allocate an inode for x,
也许它在这个时间点分配了一个 inode ，
maybe it allocates an inode at this point in time,
因为 create 是在 unlink 释放之后分配的，
well, because the create is allocating after the unlink freed,
它可能重复使用相同的 inode ，
it might reuse the same inode,
所以也许 x 会得到与 y 相同的 inode ，
so maybe x gets going to get the same inode that y had,
比如 inode 17 ，
say maybe inode 17, right,
然后，
and then,
这是可以的，因为 unlink 释放了这个 inode 。
which is okay, because unlink free this inode.
所以，看起来还不是问题，
So, doesn't look like a problem yet,
关键是，
you know the point is,
我们在试着关闭事务 1 ，
we're trying to close transaction 1,
所以，当 create 完成时，我们关闭事务 1 ，
so then when the create finishes, we close transaction 1
我们要写入，
and we're going to write,
假设事务提交，
let's say transaction actually commits,
我们将其所有修改写入磁盘。
we write all of its modifications to disk.
太棒了，
Fantastic,
不过假设 unlink 需要一段时间，还没有结束，
however supposing after the unlink takes a while hasn't finished yet,
假设提交完成后，
supposing after this commit finishes,
这里发生崩溃。
there's a crash, right.
当恢复软件运行时，
When the recovery software runs,
它将看到事务 1 已提交，
it's going to see that transaction 1 committed,
而事务 2 没有，
and that transaction two didn't,
所以恢复软件会完全忽略事务 2 ，
so the recovery software gonna just completely ignore transaction two,
所以这意味着 unlink 写入从来没有发生过，
so that means the unlink never took place it's writes,
恢复软件不会执行对磁盘的 unlink 写入，
the recovery software won't won't perform the unlink writes to the disk,
所以不会释放 inode ，
therefore won't free the inode,
不会删除 y ，
won't won't delete y,
在崩溃和恢复后 y 仍然存在，
after the crash and recovery y still exist,
它仍将使用 inode 17 ，
it will still be using inode 17,
但是 create 事务确实完成了，
however the create transaction did complete
所以 x 也将使用 inode 17 ，
and therefore x is going to be using inode 17 as well
所以，现在我们错误地有两个文件
and so now we mistakenly have two files
恰好使用相同的 inode ，
that happen to be using the same inode,
这意味着我将共享内容，
which means I'll share content
或者向其中一个文件写入，内容会神秘地出现在另一个文件中。
or write to one will mysteriously show up in the other file.
这完全是错误的，对吧。
Which is completely the wrong thing, right.
重点是我们想要 unlink y ，
The whole point was we wanted to unlink y
并使用释放的 inode x ，
and use a freed inode x,
而不是已经在使用的 inode ，
not inode that was already in use,
所以这里出了严重的问题。
so something's gone terribly wrong here.
思考这件事的一种方式是，
And you know the one way of thinking about it is
unlink 应该在事务 2 ，
that the unlink in transaction in what should have been transaction 2,
写入一个块，修改一个块，
wrote a block modified a block
本质上，修改后的块被更早的事务使用，
and essentially that modified block was used by an earlier transaction,
所以，更晚的事务修改了块，
so a later transaction, modified a block
而修改后的块被更早的事务看到，
and that modified block was seen by an earlier transaction
来自事务 2 的修改信息
and indeed information base on this modification from transaction 2
被合并到事务 1 中。
was incorporated into transaction one.
这意味着我们在这里失去了原子性，
But that means that we've lost atomicity here,
因为这件事的整个目标是，
because the whole goal of this was
unlink 的所有修改都应该发生，或者一个也不发生，
that all the modifications for the unlink should occur or none of them,
不是它们中的一部分，
not just some of them,
但这里本质上发生的是，
but what's essentially happened here is,
因为事务 1 提交了这个 inode 的空闲，
because transaction 1 committed the free of this inode,
这意味着一些修改事务发生了，
it means that some of transaction to modify modifications actually occurred,
但其他没有发生，
but others did not,
我们通过在较早的事务中包含较晚事务的写入打破了原子性。
we broke atomicity by including a later transaction's write in an earlier transaction.
你可以想象有多种不同的方式来处理这个，
And you can actually imagine multiple different ways of dealing with this, right,
也许 create 可以注意到 17 是被一个未来的事务释放了的，
maybe create could notice that 17 had been freed by a you know a future transaction
并且不使用这个 inode ，
and not use that inode,
事实上， ext3 对此采取了非常简单的方法，
in fact ext3 takes a pretty simple approach to this,
它不允许启动任何系统调用，
it doesn't allow any system call to start
直到来自前一事务的所有系统调用都已完成，
until all system calls from the previous transaction have finished,
所以，这不可能，
so there's no possibility of a transaction,
事务的系统调用看到修改，
a system call from transaction when seeing a modify,
看到来自未来事务系统调用的更新。
seeing an update from a system call the future transaction.
本质上， unlink 被阻塞，
Essentially, all of the unlink is pushed, is blocked
在 t1 提交之前不允许开始。
not allowed to start until t1 commits.
对于这个，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this?
所以我有一个问题，
So I have a question about
当你关闭一个打开的事务时，到底会发生什么，
what exactly happens, when you close an open transaction,
它是否像快照，
does it like snapshot,
比如当前状态缓存。
like the current state of like the cache.
是的，完全正确，
Yes, that's exactly right,
所以，当我们关闭这个事务时，
so when we close this transaction,
至少在原则上，
at least in principle,
系统会复制所有的块，
the system makes a copy of all the blocks,
在这个事务中系统调用所修改的块，
that were modified by system calls in this transaction,
日志系统将它们复制到缓存中，
logging system makes a copy of them in the cache,
这是一种仅用于事务提交它们的私有副本。
sort of private copy just for this transaction commit them.
然后，未来的事务在实际缓存的块上执行某种操作，
And then future transactions execute sort of on the real cached blocks,
这个事务从其修改的块的私有副本进行提交。
this transaction commits from its private copy of the blocks it modified.
然后，当它完成提交这些私有数据块复制到磁盘后，
And then when it's done committing those it's private copy those blocks to disk,
可以把那些复制扔掉。
you can throw those copies away.
是的。
Yes.
好的。
Okay.
这个，这是
There's, it turns out this is
大约六个或十几个类似的小的怪事之一，
one of about half a dozen or a dozen sort of similar little quirks,
ext3 必须解决，
that ext3 has to deal with,
因为为了支持并发，
because in order to support concurrency,
有一大堆类似的排序的琐事，
there's a whole bunch of kind of similar little ordering niggles,
这是 ext3 必须正确处理的特殊情况，
that have to be the special cases that ext3 has to get right,
我们没时间讨论这个，
which we don't have time to talk about,
但是要点，
but the take home points
我想人们记住的关于日志 ext3 的，
that I want people to remember about logging about ext3,
首先，一般的观点，
first, the general point that,
日志是关于使多步磁盘更新成为原子的，
what logs are all about is making multi-step disk updates atomic,
对于崩溃，全部发生或全部没有，
all or nothing with respect to crashes,
这是关于日志最需要记住的一件事，
like, yeah, that's the main thing to remember about logging,
日志的正确性取决于预写规则。
the logging the correctness of logging depends on the write-ahead rule.
另一件需要记住的重要事情是，
It's another critical thing to remember
你会经常听到预写日志和预写规则，
you'll hear write-ahead log and write-ahead rule a lot
在崩溃恢复业务中。
in the kind of crash recovery business.
预写规则规定
And the write-ahead rule says that
你必须提交对日志的所有更改，
you have to commit all changes to the log,
在允许对主位置进行任何修改之前，
before you're allowed to make any of the modifications to the home locations
在文件系统中。
in the file system.
而且恢复也依赖于这条规则，
And recovery absolutely relies on this rule,
很多要点，
a lot of the point,
至少对于文件系统，
at least for file systems,
日志的要点是简单快速恢复，
a lot of the point of logging is simply fast recovery,
日志中可能有几百个块，
log may have a couple hundred blocks in it,
你可以在不到一秒的时间里重放几百个块，
you can replay a couple hundred blocks in way under a second
然后启动你的文件系统，
and then boom your file system,
即使是一个非常大的，现在也可以使用了。
even a very large one is, now fit for use.
现在，最后关于 ext3 的更详细的一点是，
Now the final point for a more detailed point about the ext3 is
它使用批处理和并发
that it uses batching and concurrency
来获得比 xv6 好得多的性能，
to get considerably better performance than xv6 does,
尽管在很高的复杂性的情况下，
although at the case of considerable considerably higher complexity,
为了支持比 xv6 更高的并发。
to support concurrency than xv6 has.
今天就到这里，
And that's all for today,
我很高兴回答大家的问题。
I'm happy to take questions.
嗯，嗨，我还有一个问题是关于，
Um, hi, I had another question is about,
所以你说，
so you said that,
靠着有一个文件系统调用，
thinks that there's a file system
文件系统线程来做所有这些事情，
like a file system thread that does all this stuff,
这些线程中必须只有一个，
there must be only one of these threads,
否则它可以完成刚才所说的事情。
because otherwise it could it could do basically what it just talked about, right.
可能确实只有一个，
It may indeed be that there's just one,
我其实不知道有多少个，
I actually don't know how many there are,
一当然是一个特别有吸引力的数字，
one is certainly a particularly attractive number,
因为日志是正确的很多基本原理是，
because you know a lot of the rationale for why the logging is correct is
较旧的事务在较新的事务之前提交，
that you know the older transactions or you know committed before newer transactions,
我不认为这是只有一个线程的合乎逻辑的必然性，
I I don't think it's a logical necessity that there be only one thread,
你可以想象，旧的事务以重叠的方式提交，
so you could imagine, old transactions committing in an overlapped way,
本质上是使用多个线程，每个事务一个线程。
you know essentially using multiple threads, one for each transaction.
好的，我明白了。
Oh, okay, I see.
好的，我知道了。
Okay, I see.
我有个问题，
I have a question,
当你谈论崩溃的时候，
in when you're talking about crashes
你有一张 t8 重写 t5 的图，
and you had that diagram of t8 rewriting t5
它正在被释放，
that was being freed,
那么，如果 t8 在崩溃时没有真正被提交，会发生什么，
so what happens if t8 hasn't actually committed at the point of the crash,
因为可能 t5 ，
because there could be maybe t5,
如果它因为需要重写而被释放的话，
if it's being freed as something needs to rewrite it,
那么可能存在来自 t5 的提交块，
then there could be a commit block from t5 that exists,
它可能是 t8 预测它存在的位置，
it may be a location where t8 would have predicted it to exist,
那么这是不是能准确地表示
and then couldn't that inaccurately represent
t8 已经被提交了吗？
that t8 was actually had actually been committed.
好的，让我试着画出出这个场景，
Okay, so let me try to draw out the scenario,
所以我们有这个古老的事务 t5 ，
so we have this ancient transaction t5, right,
也许这里是 t6 ，
and you know maybe t6 here,
然后绕回来是 t8 ，
and then we're, you've wrapped around t8,
t8 现在开始在某个地方，
and you know t8 started somewhere now,
因为 t5 是空闲的，
it's because t5 is free,
t8 开始增长，
t8 is starting the eat up,
t5 是，
t5 that is,
t8 的末尾超过 t5 的开始。
the end of t8 is overrun the beginning of t5 is that.
好的，令人担忧的是，
Okay, and the worry is,
好的，当然如果 t8 提交了，
okay, of course if t8 did commit,
然后它将以提交块结束，
then it'll end up in a commit block,
而且看起来都很合理，
and it all look pretty reasonable,
如果恢复出现崩溃，
if there's a crash in recovery
而担心的情况是 t8 没有提交。
and the scenario worried about t8 did not commit.
是的。
Right.
是的，好的，
Yeah, okay,
所以，[]确实如此，
so the [] yeah exactly,
所以 t8 碰巧会把它的提交块放在
so t8, t8 just happens to be going to put its commit block
和 t5 放提交块完全相同的地方，
in exactly the same place where t5 puts commit block,
但是它没有写入提交块，
but it didn't quite get the write the commit block,
所有都是好的，除了，
it's all good, except,
我们有一个完全正确的 t8 ，
this we have a totally correct t8,
但它是 t5 的提交块。
but it's t5's commit block.
嗯。
Yeah.
你在想，
You're wondering,
天哪，看起来像一个提交块，
gosh looks just like a commit block,
好的，答案是
okay, the answer is that
描述符块和提交块
the descriptor blocks and commit blocks
以及其他所有内容都具有事务的序列号，
as well as everything else have the sequence number of the transactions,
所以这个描述符块有一个 8 ，
so this descriptor block has an 8 in it,
但是 t5 的提交描述符，
and but t5's commit descriptor, doesn't matter,
但是 t5 提交块中有一个 5 。
but t5 commit block has a 5 in it.
好的，好的。
Okay, yeah.
是的，它查看 8 像魔术数一样。
And so yeah it's looking 8 as well as the magic number.
好问题。
Good question.
等等，但在这种情况下，
Wait, but in this case,
你也有 t5 的描述符块，
would you also have the descriptor block of t5,
所以你并不需要这些数字。
so you don't really need the numbers.
嗯，在这个特殊的案例中，
Well, in this particular case,
t5 过去有一个描述符块，里面有一个 5 ，
so yeah t5 used to have a descriptor block here, with a 5 in it,
然而， t8 太大，
however t8 is so large,
t8 重写了描述符块，
that t8 overwrote this descriptor block,
使用它自己的数据块。
with one of its own data blocks.
所以 t5 描述符块就没了，
So that t5 descriptor blocks have gone
取而代之的是 t8 的块。
and been replaced by t8 block.
所以，是的，曾经是事务 5 ，
So, yeah used to be evidence for transaction 5,
但现在它不见了。
but now it's now it's gone.
那么，在我们开始之前，我们知道事务 8 的大小吗？
So do we know the size of transaction 8 before we started.
嗯。
Mhm mm, um.
抱歉，这是个复杂的问题，
Sorry, this is a complex question,
很可能是，
the it's probably the case that ex- that,
好的，当 t8 作为活动事务打开时，
okay, when t8 was opened as the active transaction,
系统调用正在写入，
the system calls were writing into
在那个时间点上，
at that point in time,
系统不知道 t8 会有多大，
the system didn't know how big t8 was going to be,
当系统开始提交 t8 时，
when the system starts committing t8,
它确实知道 t8 是多少，
it does know, it does know, it does know how t8 be t8 is,
系统没有开始提交 t8 ，
the system doesn't start committing t8,
在 t8 关闭之后，
until after t8 is closed,
它的所有系统调用都已完成。
all of its system calls are finished.
在这一点上，系统知道，
And at that point the system knows,
我的意思是，所有的写入都已完成，
I mean it's all the writes that were done,
t8 的所有写入都已完成，
all the writes for t8 have completed,
所有的系统调用都已完成，
all the system calls are completed,
所以系统知道它有多大。
so the system knows how big it is.
必须这样做的一个原因是，
One reason why that must be is that
描述符块持有该事务中的完整块列表，
the descriptor block holds the complete list of blocks in that transaction
所以在描述符块写入的时候，
and so at the time the descriptor block was written,
这是第一次，日志系统知道
which is first the logging system knew
我们将在 t8 中有多少个块。
how many blocks that we're going to be in t8.
是的。
Yeah.
哦，好的，我知道了，
Oh, okay, I see, I see,
谢谢。
thank you.
为什么我们不
Why don't we just kind of
把提交信息放到描述符块中来避免这类问题，
like have the commit information into the descriptor block and avoid this kind of problem,
我知道这不太好，
because I know I know it's not great,
我们必须回去，
that we have to go back
比如不是按顺序写入的，
and like write back to the location, like not in sequence,
但那会不会有帮助？
but wouldn't that help?
好的，所以建议是，
Okay, so the proposal is that,
与其有一个提交块，
instead of having a commit block,
我们让描述符块当作提交块，
we basically have the descriptor block act as a commit block
而且 xv6 与此非常相似。
and xv6 actually is very much like this.
你知道你能这样做，
And I, you know you could do it,
事实上，我认为你能这样做，
and and and in fact I think you can do it,
至少 ext3 不降低效率，
without at least an ext3 without sacrificing efficiency,
然而，你必须同样，
however, you have to play the same,
你必须以与 xv6 相同的方式构建它，
you have to structure this in the same way that xv6 does,
也就是说，
namely you, you, you,
如果有一个，
if there's a,
你必须在描述符块中有一些东西，
you have to be something in the descriptor block,
表明这是一个提交事务，
that indicates this is a commit transaction
我们不允许设置任何标志，
and we're not allowed to set whatever that flag is,
在所有数据块写入之前，
until after all of the data blocks have been written,
所以顺序是，
so the routine would have to be,
我们不先写提交挡路，
we don't write the commit block first,
相反，我们首先写入事务 8 的所有数据块，
instead we write all the data blocks for transaction 8 first,
然后我们回去写下提交块和块编号，
and then we go back and write the commit block with the block numbers,
这个描述符块，不管它现在是什么，
with a descriptor block, whatever it is now
还有某种魔力，这是一个提交的事务。
and some kind of magic, this is really a committed transaction.
所以我们可以写入所有数据块，
So we can write all the data blocks
然后返回并写入提交块，
and then go back and write the commit block,
这个描述符提交块，不管是什么，
that descriptor commit block, whatever,
我不知道，
I don't know any,
我不知道为什么这个不能工作。
I don't know any reason why this couldn't be made to work.
我不认为它，
It I I don't think it,
它没有，
it doesn't,
我认为它没有真正消除我们讨论过的任何问题，
I don't think it really eliminates any of the problems we've discussed,
因为我们还有这个问题，
because we still have this problem,
最初的问题是，
the original problem was,
天哪，我们如何区分这个提交块，
gosh how do we distinguish this commit block,
这个来自事务 5 的旧提交块，
this stale commit block from transaction 5
来自事务 8 的真实提交块，
from a true commit block for transaction 8,
我们在这里也会遇到同样的问题，
we're going to have the same problem here,
这可能是在这里的东西，
you know this it could be that what's sitting here,
恰好是事务 5 中的描述符块。
you know just happens to be the descriptor block from transaction 5.
所以，也许我们继续，
And so you know maybe we've gone ahead
写入事务的所有数据块，
and written all the data blocks for transaction data
然后发生了崩溃，
and then there was a crash,
恢复软件仍然需要能够区分，
the recovery software still needs to be able to tell the difference between,
查看这个描述符块，
to be able to look at this descriptor block
然后等一下，
and say wait a minute,
这里有些不对劲，
you know there's something wrong here,
尽管这看起来是一个有效的描述符块，
even though this looks like a valid descriptor block,
但实际上并非如此。
it's not really.
所以我们仍然需要魔术数，
And so we still have to have the magic number
事务号，序列号。
and the transaction number, the sequence number.
哦，是的，理解了，
Oh, yeah, that makes sense,
是的，我只是在想，
yeah, I was just thinking,
比如我们应该有，
like we'd have,
我们提交描述符块的一部分，
we kind of have like to commit part in the description block,
但很明显，当我们开始 t8 时，
but obviously like when we start t8,
我们写入描述符块，它是未提交的，
we write the description block saying it's uncommitted,
然后我们写入数据块，
then we write the data blocks,
那么我们现在就说它是一个提交块。
then we say it's a committed block, now.
这里可以节省的是
The thing that could be saved here is
等待这些写入的花费，
the expense of waiting for these writes
然后写入一个提交块，
and then writing a commit block right,
等待的花费很高，
that wait is quite expensive,
我们不允许开始写入提交块，
we're not allowed to start the write of the commit block
直到数据块位于磁盘上，
until the data blocks are on the disk
我不认为，
and I I I don't think,
我们必须有相同的等待，
we have to have the same wait before we end here,
在新的单个块方案中，
in this sort of new single block scheme,
我们必须有相同的等待，
we have to have the same wait,
在我们写入这个新的描述符块之前，
before we're allowed to write this new descriptor block,
所以它省了一个块，
so it saves a block,
但是我不认为它省了时间。
but it doesn't save, I don't think I would save much time.
技巧，
The trick I,
更高版本的 Linux 文件系统的技巧，
the trick that later versions of the Linux file system play that,
确实达到了你想要的效果。
sort of does do what I think you're hoping for.
你知道，
You know the the,
查看 ext4 完成了以下（操作）
this is looking into the ext4 does the following
用来更高效地写入提交块。
for better efficiency of writing the commit blocks.
ext4 同时写入所有数据块和提交块，
It ext4 will write out the all the data blocks and the commit block at the same time,
也就是说，它不等待，
that is it doesn't wait,
数据块写入完成，在写入提交块之前，
for the data block writes to finish before writes the commit block,
所以它不会有这么长的暂停时间，
so it doesn't have this long pause,
但是有一个严重的问题，
but then there's this terrible issue,
如果磁盘，
what happens if the disk,
磁盘盘可以自由地进行无序写入，
the disk is free to do writes out of order,
如果磁盘首先写入提交块，
what if the disk writes the commit block first,
在它执行数据块写入之前，
before it actually performs the writes for the data blocks
然后发生崩溃，
and then there's a crash,
然后我们有一个提交块，
then we have a commit block
而没有写入的数据块，
without having to discover having written the data blocks
而 ext4 解决这个问题的方式，
and the way ext4 solves that,
它在提交块中有一个校验和，
is it has a checksum in the commit block,
对所有数据块进行校验和。
over a checksum over all the data blocks.
所以，如果在写入提交块后发生崩溃，
And so if there's a crash happens after the commit block was written,
在写入数据块之前，
before the data blocks were written,
校验和将不起作用。
the checksum won't work out.
恢复软件查看校验和，
The recovery software look at this checksum
然后它计算日志中数据块的校验和，
and then it'll compute the checksum over the data blocks that are actually in the log,
如果它们不相同，
if they're not the same,
它就知道出了问题。
it knows that something went wrong.
所以，通过这样做，
And so by doing this,
ext4 在机械硬盘上，节省了一个旋转，
ext4 basically saves on a mechanical drive saves an entire rotations,
它会发生，
that would happen,
如果必须在提交之前等待数据块。
if it had to wait for the data blocks before it commits.
好的，谢谢。
Okay, thanks.
哦，太酷了。
Oh that's cool.
我喜欢这些东西。
I love this stuff.
这太酷了，
This is very cool,
我还想问一下数据块，
I wanted to ask also about the data blocks,
只是内容块。
just the content blocks.
所以我想疑问的，
So I think I got confused,
但是在我们讨论的步骤中，
but where in the steps that we were talking about,
在你之前的一块板上，
on your one of your previous boards,
那个是在哪里做的？
where would that be done?
在哪里哪个做呢？
Where would which be done.
所以，不是元数据块，而是实际的。
So like, not the metadata blocks, but the actual.
文件内容，
File content,
alright, okay this is, sort of multiple answers to this,
在 ext3 中有多种模式，
in ext3 has multiple modes,
对于数据块发生的情况，
for what happens to the data blocks,
我记得有两三个，
I think there's three or two of which I remember,
有日志数据和顺序数据，
there's journal data and order data, in the,
当你配置 ext3 文件系统时，
and when you configure an ext3 file system,
你告诉 Linux 你想要什么，
you tell Linux which you want,
如果你要求日志数据，
if you ask for journal data,
文件内容只是直接写入日志，
then file content just goes write into the log,
没有什么特别的，
there's nothing special going on,
如果你将数据写入文件，
if you write data to a file
引起 inode 更新，
and that causes the inode to be updated,
然后日志将包含你的数据，
then the log is gonna contain your data
并更新 inode ，
and the updated an inode,
所有被修改的东西都会记入日志，
you know everything, everything gets modified goes in the log,
那就是日志数据。
that's journal data.
当然，它很慢，
But, of course it's quite slow
或者比你想象的要慢，
or slower than you might hope,
因为，
because you know,
如果你写一整串数据，
now if you write a whole bunch of data,
它必须写一次到日志，
it has to be written once to the log
然后第二次到原位置，
and then a second time to the home location,
所以，日志数据方案简单明了，但速度很慢。
so the journal data scheme is straightforward, but slow.
然后，还有另一种顺序数据方案，
Then there's this other order data scheme,
那就是人们最流行的模式，
that people that's actually the most popular mode,
避免，不将数据写入日志，
avoid, that doesn't write the data to the log,
在顺序数据方案中，
in the order data scheme,
只有像 inode 和目录块这样的元数据才会写入日志，
only metadata like inodes and directory blocks are written to the log
而文件内容块直接写入文件系统中的原位置，
and file content block is just written directly to the home locations in the file system
所以它的速度要快得多，
and so it's a lot faster,
因为你不必写入文件内容两次，
because you don't have to write the file content twice,
这确实会导致更复杂的情况，
it does lead to more complexity though,
因为如果，
because if you,
你不能随时写文件数据，
you can't just write the file data anytime you want,
因为这样会有风险，
because then there's a risk that,
如果你不担心你写 inode 的顺序，
if you don't worry about the order in which you write the inodes,
文件数据存在这样的风险，
there's the file data, there's the risk,
你可能执行写入操作，
that you might do a write,
导致为文件分配新的块，
that causes a new block to be allocated for file
并将更新后的 inode 写入日志并提交，
and have the updated inode be written into the log and committed
然后发生崩溃，
and then have a crash happen,
在你写入实际文件内容到磁盘之前，
before you get around to writing the actual file content to the disk,
然后在恢复之后，
and then after recovery,
你将看到的是，
what you would see is
包含新分配的数据块的 inode ，
the inode with the new newly allocated data block,
但是数据块的旧内容
but the old contents of that data block
来自之前使用该数据块的文件，
from whatever file previously used that data block,
所以，如果你运行的系统有多个用户，比如 Athena ，
and so if you're running a system that has multiple users, like Athena system,
可能是一个用户最终
then it could be that one user will end up
拥有的文件包含另一个用户已删除文件的内容。
having a file that contains contents from another user's deleted file.
如果我们不注意顺序，
If we're not careful about the order
写入数据与 inode 的顺序。
in which we write the data versus the inode.
ext3 顺序数据模式解决这个，
A ext3 order data mode solves this,
通过不提交修改的 inode ，
by not committing a modified inode
直到文件内容写入磁盘之后，
until after the file content has been written to disk,
所以，如果你的应用程序写入文件，
so if your application and you write to a file
那个写入导致分配新的块，
and that write causes a new block to be allocated,
文件系统将新文件内容写入新分配的块，
the file system will write the new file content to the newly allocated block,
一旦写入完成，
and once that write is finished,
它才会提交事务。
only then will it commit the transaction.
这导致 inode 更新为包含新的块编号，
That causes the inode to be updated to have the new block number
这意味着，崩溃，
and that means that a crash,
如果崩溃发生在，
if there's a crash is going to happen
写入数据时，
between when you wrote the data,
写入数据之后和写入 inode 之前，
after you wrote the data and before you wrote the inode,
不会显示别人删除的旧数据块
therefore won't reveal somebody else's old deleted data block
给新用户文件。
to the new user file.
好的，我明白了。
Okay, I see.
好的，我明白了，
Okay, I see,
但是它仍然可以有数据，而没有 inode 。
but it could still have the data, but not the inode.
是的，你可能分配。
Yeah, you might allocate.
是的，如果发生崩溃，
Yeah, it was a crash,
在你写入数据块之后，写入 inode 之前，
after you after you wrote the data block before you wrote the inode,
那么你已经更新了数据块，
then you have updated the data block,
但这并不重要，
but it doesn't matter,
因为你不仅没有写 inode ，
because not only did you not write the inode,
你也没有写更新块，空闲位图块，
you also didn't write the updated block, free bitmap block,
块是空闲的，并且可以分配给其他东西，
blocks will be free and could be allocated for something else,
所以一个块都不会丢。
so would not even lose a block.
好的，如果是老块，
Alright, and if it's an old block,
那还是可以的，对吧。
then it's still okay, right.
再说一遍。
Say it again.
如果只是，
If it was just,
它是一样的块，写入新的数据，
it is the same, the same block just write some new data to it,
但是一样的块，一样的大小，一样的位置，
but same block, same size, same same location,
但是我们已经写入，
but we already wrote,
比如不是我们创建一个新的块，
like it's not that we created a new block,
而是在旧的块，我们写入一些额外的数据，
but in the old block, we just wrote some extra data,
但它有一点，
but it was a little bit,
所以它不需要创造一个新的。
so it didn't need to create a new one.
是的，我们写入数据，
Yeah, we wrote data,
我们最终将数据写入块中，
we ended up writing to a data to a block,
它没有被任何文件使用，
that was not in use by any file,
它是不可见的。
it's not visible.
好的，我明白了，
Right, okay I see,
谢谢。再见。
thank you, goodbye.